<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations concerning money and coin and especially those of England</title>
            <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L755B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O94_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27300561</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27300561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1724:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations concerning money and coin and especially those of England</title>
                  <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Buck ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XC VII [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Henry Layton.</note>
                  <note>This item formerly identified as Wing O94 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Currency question --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Coinage --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110068:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS CONCERNING Money and Coin, And eſpecially thoſe of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, for <hi>Peter Buck</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> near the <hi>Inner-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:110068:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110068:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>COmmon Experience convinces, That when People are fallen into Swounds, or under the torpor of a Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Drowſineſs, a ſudden ſharp cry or piercing Noiſe made about them will recover them out of their Swounds, or waken or ſtir them up from ſuch Lethargick Drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, imparting to them as great a proportion of Life and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour as the ſtrength of their Natures and Conſtitutions are able to act or endure.</p>
            <p>The Writer of this Pamphlet hath for ſome Years lain under the ſtupor of Age and divers Maladies; and though during the last Winter he heard divers Diſcourſes and Complaints concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money Matters, and read divers Pamphlets concerning that Subject, which by ſeveral Friends were communicated to him; yet he was little moved therewithal, but let them paſs without much Scruple or careful Search into the Merits of them, but now lately, <hi>viz.</hi> in the latter end of <hi>May, Anno 1696.</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came alarm'd by the ſharp Cries of his Countrey, and the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Towns, and thoſe of his own Family upon ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; this rouſed him from the Stupor of his Age, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering under divers Diſeaſes; he remembred a Prophets Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, <hi>Let the Weak ſay I am Strong,</hi> and that in Caſes of neceſſity, there is no exception of Old or Young: But all muſt
<pb facs="tcp:110068:3"/>draw to Arms for the Defence and Preſervation of their Native Country, and thereupon he furbiſh'd up his diſuſed Weapons, and Instruments, his Pen and Paper; requeſting of his Friends a review of ſuch Pamphlets as he had before returned them. And becauſe he apprehended that the lightening of our preſent Coin might be very beneficial to the Kingdom, he deſired moſt a review of thoſe Papers, which maintained the contrary; upon this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, a Friend ſent him the Merchant of <hi>Amſterdam</hi>'s Letter, alſo Mr. <hi>Lock</hi>'s Book and his two Letters about Gold and Silver, and thereupon he ſate down Armed to take a review and a fuller Examination of them, and that Examination and the Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a Refutation of their Arguments, is the principal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Treatiſe; he thinks not fit to delay the Publication of it till a next ſitting of the Parliament; but chuſes rather to Print it with the moſt early convenience, that a large time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſitting of the Parliament, may be given for the Peruſal and Trial of matters therein propoſed; that all Men, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Members of both Houſes may have leiſure and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to execute the Direction given by the <hi>Levite</hi> in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> viz. <hi>Conſider of it, take advice and ſpeak your minds, conſider of it by your ſelves, ponder it well, and ruminate upon it, the Matter being of great Importance and Concern;</hi> next take advice by Diſcourſe and Conference with others, and the Ventilation of Arguments on both ſides; that lastly, when they meet together in Parliament, they may be able and ready to ſpeak their Minds, knowingly, freely, and with ſuch degrees of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as may be reaſonable; whence there may be hoped a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation may ſpeedily follow of our preſent Grievances, the greateſt which have fallen upon the Nation ſince the <hi>long Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was Diſolved. There will (no doubt) be many Errors and Eſcapes found in this Pamphlet, both in the Matter and in the Manner, and in Printing of it; all which the Judicious Peruſers are prayed to amend, or paſs by with gentleneſs, conſidering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, leſt they alſo be tempted to come under the Cenſure of others, upon this ſame Subject, or any other the like occaſions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110068:3"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS CONCERNING MONEY and COYN And eſpecially thoſe OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>THE Practice of our Times directs to fabricate the Knowledge of Arts, Things, and Science, upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and the Relations or Hiſtories of former Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, and ſuch as later and our Times have found, tried, and ſuperadded to them; and hence Men may be induced reaſonably to reflect upon the Practices of former Ages concerning Money, and that will enforce ſhortly to deliver a ſort of Hiſtory relating to our preſent Subject.</p>
            <p>The Bible ſeems reaſonably accounted an Hiſtory the moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in the World, or at leaſt of any that is yet known to our parts of it, with acceptance;</p>
            <p>There we read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. That <hi>Abraham</hi> was born 292 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Flood; and Cap. 23. That he was 137 years old at the death of <hi>Sarah:</hi> And that upon her death, he bought a Burying place for her of <hi>Ephron,</hi> and paid for it 400 Shekels of Silver, Currant Money with the Merchant, meaſured as well by weight, as number of the pieces; Cap. 24. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant adorn'd <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110068:4"/>with a Golden Ear-Ring of half a Shekel weight, and two Golden Bracelets of ten Shekels weight; Cap. 13. ſays, that <hi>Abraham</hi> went up out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and was then very Rich in Silver, and in Gold; theſe Texts prove that Metles of Silver and Gold were in thoſe Times the meaſures of other Commodities and their Values: alſo that they were ſomewhat plentiful, and were then uſed amongſt Merchants, and Traders, Coyned into known pieces of Money, and meaſurable as well by weight as by tale and number of the pieces: Cap. 23, <hi>Jacob</hi> bought a parcel of a Field for an 100 pieces of Money, and Cap. 37. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethen ſold him to the <hi>Iſhmalitiſh</hi> Merchants for twenty pieces of Silver. Cap. 42. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s Sons went to buy Corn, <hi>Joſeph</hi> commands to fill their Sacks and to reſtore every Mans Money into his Sack. Cap. 43. The ſame again; Cap. 45 <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent to <hi>Benjamin</hi> five Changes of Rayment, and 300 pieces of Silver; and Cap. 47. <hi>Joſeph</hi> gathered all the Money that was found in the Land of <hi>Aegypt</hi> for Corn. Theſe Texts prove abundantly the common uſe of Gold and Silver, and the Cutting and Coyning them into Money for the more Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Trading and Trafficking in the World, from the firſt Times and Ages of it. And the ſame Uſage and Cuſtom may be ſo eaſily carried on and brought down to our own time by a conſtant Tenor and Courſe of Hiſtories, that it would appear but a loſs of time in writing, and an abuſe of patience in reading, if any farther progreſs ſhould be made to that purpoſe: Therefore let us proceed to more particular Hiſtory concerning the uſages of Gold Silver and Money in our own Native Countrey of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the reſearch of it, it ſeems we muſt ſubmit to a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeas for all former Times and Ages before thoſe wherein <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> made our Countrey known to the <hi>Roman</hi> World; and ſince that time we find by Mr. <hi>Speed</hi> in his Chronicle (in which we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he hath uſed much ſearch and diligence) that ſome Brittiſh Princes did Coyn ſome pieces both of Gold and Silver, of which he there exhibits to us the <hi>Specimina,</hi> viz of <hi>Caſſibelan,</hi> who princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally oppos'd the Conqueſt then intended by <hi>Julius Caeſar;</hi> next, a Coyn of <hi>Cunobelin</hi> or <hi>Kymbeline</hi> Son of <hi>Thomantius</hi> and Grand-child of <hi>Caſſibelan,</hi> in the time of <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> And that <hi>Kymbelines</hi> own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage was ſtamped upon the Coyn, after the manner of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> concerning which our Lord demands <hi>whoſe Image and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is this?</hi> Then he exhibits to us the Coyns of <hi>Arviragus,</hi> and <hi>Galgacus,</hi> Britiſh Kings in the time of the Emperor <hi>Domitian</hi> before which time, <hi>viz.</hi> in the time of <hi>Nero: Agricola</hi> Lieutenant of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> in <hi>Britain</hi> had Conquer'd our whole Iſland, and reduced <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110068:4"/>into the form of a <hi>Roman</hi> Province, which the <hi>Romans</hi> held under their Yoak and Dominion from that time, <hi>viz.</hi> about <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 60, until the Reign of the Emperor <hi>Honorius</hi> about <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 400. which is the ſpace of 340 years, during all which time it appears with clearneſs, our Predeceſſors the <hi>Britains</hi> uſed the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Coyns and Money, and before the <hi>Roman</hi> times, both <hi>Speed</hi> and <hi>Camden</hi> do agree with ſome <hi>Roman</hi> Authors, that the <hi>Britains</hi> uſed no other Money in their Payments, but Rings of Iron, and ſome Plates or pieces of Braſs. If we enquire concerning the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Roman</hi> Money of thoſe Times, we may be informed by <hi>Pliny</hi> in his Natural Hiſtory, <hi>Lib.</hi> 33. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. There he tells us that he could never learn who was the firſt, that by ſetting a Stamp upon Gold, ordained it to paſs for Money, but he is ſure that the People of <hi>Rome</hi> had neither Gold nor Silver Money ſtamped before the Victories, which they had over <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> King of <hi>Epirus;</hi> and he knows that in old time of their Government, their manner was to weigh out Braſs by the As, which was a pound weight, and thence was call'd <hi>As libralis;</hi> and the Soldiers Wages were ſo paid, <hi>viz.</hi> by weight, and thence called <hi>Stipendia;</hi> and at this day (about <hi>Anuo Chriſti</hi> 120) he ſays, in all buyings and ſellings, which paſs with warranty, the payment paſſes uſually by interpoſition of the Ballance; and that ſerves to teſtifie the reallity of the Contract on both parts; for the <hi>Roman</hi> Braſs Money, it was firſt ſtamped by <hi>Servius Tullius,</hi> one of their firſt Kings; before which time it was uſed at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Maſs or Lump, by weight, his Stamp upon ſuch Braſs Money was the Figure or Form of a Sheep, in Latin term'd <hi>Pecus,</hi> and thence proceeded the word <hi>pecunia;</hi> and during that King's Reign, the richeſt Man in <hi>Rome</hi> was valued not to be worth more in Goods than an 110000 <hi>Aſſes</hi> of Braſs.</p>
            <p>Five years before the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> War, the <hi>Romans</hi> began to ſtamp Silver Money; and then it was ordained, that the Silver <hi>Denarius</hi> ſhould go for ten <hi>Aſſes</hi> or pounds of Braſs; the half <hi>Dena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> or <hi>Quinarius</hi> for five ſuch <hi>Aſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Sexterce</hi> for two and an half: But that Punick War put the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth ſo much behind hand, that it was Agreed, and Ordain'd to raiſe the value of the Brazen Money, by diminiſhing the weight of it; ſo that whereas before, the <hi>Aſs</hi> weighed a pound of 12 ounces now they brought down the <hi>Aſs</hi> to the weight of 2 ounces; by which device, ſays he, the Commonwealth gained five parts in ſix; and the publick Treaſury was, by this means, ſoon acquitted of all Debts: And when in the ſecond Punick War, <hi>Rome</hi> was greatly diſtreſt by <hi>Hanibal,</hi> and ſorely put to it for Money to maintain
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110068:5"/>that War, they brought down their later <hi>Aſs</hi> from the weight of 2 ounces to 1 ounce; and the value of their Silver <hi>Denarius</hi> they raiſed from 10 <hi>Aſſes</hi> to 16 <hi>Aſſes;</hi> the <hi>Quinaaius</hi> to 8, and the <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terce</hi> to 4, and by this means, he ſays, the State gained very near the half, but excepts Soldiers Wages, wherein the <hi>Denarius</hi> was to paſs but for 10 <hi>Aſſes</hi> as before; he ſays, There was no Gold Coyned till 62 years after the Coyning of Silver, and the Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Gold pieces was, at firſt, of 50 pieces to a pound weight; and that Proportion was diminiſhed in weight by little and little, till by <hi>Nero</hi> it was brought to be Coyned at 55 pieces to the pound weight; This of <hi>Roman</hi> Coyns.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Romans</hi> departure out of <hi>Britain</hi> in the Reign of the Emperor <hi>Honorius,</hi> until the Subverſion of the Britiſh Nation by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the Britiſh Money and Coyn ſeems to have continued in the ſame State wherein the <hi>Romans</hi> leſt it.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Britains,</hi> and firſt King <hi>Vortimer,</hi> called in the <hi>Saxons</hi> to his Aid againſt the Northern Men, who ſtood out againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and now pillaged and ſubdued their deſerted Provinces: To <hi>Vortigern</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Vortimer, Anno</hi> 454. and then <hi>Aurelius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ther, Arthur,</hi> &amp;c. unto <hi>Cadwolloder,</hi> who b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gan to Reign <hi>Anno</hi> 685. but his Power at that time only reached to the Countrey of <hi>Wales,</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> having driven the <hi>Brittains</hi> into thoſe Mountains long before that time. The Reign of <hi>Arthur</hi> is by <hi>Speed</hi> placed to begin <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 516. and that it extended to 542. at which time, he ſays, the <hi>Saxons</hi> had ſpread themſelves as far as to <hi>Tine</hi> in the North, <hi>Anno</hi> 578. <hi>Vortiporus</hi> ſucceeded King of the <hi>Brittains,</hi> called by <hi>Gildas,</hi> Tyrant of <hi>South Wales,</hi> which Obſervations have been uſed, for the Collecting a likely Commencement for the eſtabliſhing the <hi>Saxon</hi> Government in the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> which ſeems to be ſoon after <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Death, and may be moſt probably placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno-Chriſti</hi> 550. betwixt which year of Commencement and our own time, two Periods ſeem requiſite to be obſerved; the firſt of them from <hi>Anno</hi> 550. until the Reign of King <hi>Hen.</hi> the 3d, whoſe Reign began <hi>anno</hi> 1216. which is a ſpace of about 660 years; and the 2d from 1260. to 1696, the ſpace of 436 years.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe Periods we have no ſuch certain Rule to Calculate the value of our Money by, as we may find under the ſecond Period; but muſt be forced to Collect upon Inferences, the likelieſt approaches to the Truth of ſuch values.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speed</hi> in his Chronicle fol. 225. and 288. ſays, That <hi>Cherdeck</hi> was the firſt <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> King, ſucceeded by his Son <hi>Kenrick,</hi> and he by his Son <hi>Ceoline,</hi> who began to Reign <hi>Anno</hi> 561. to him our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110068:5"/>Author aſcribes a Silver Coyn here exemplified; that <hi>Edward</hi> King of the <hi>Eaſt. Angles</hi> Coyned Money <hi>Anno</hi> 616. and <hi>Aldolph</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland Anno</hi> 664, and then alſo <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of <hi>Kent;</hi> then <hi>Offa</hi> of <hi>Mercia Anno</hi> 758. then <hi>Kenwolf</hi> of <hi>Mercia</hi> 794. <hi>Egbert</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarch <hi>Anno</hi> 800. <hi>Berwulf</hi> of <hi>Mercia Anno</hi> 821. but no more till 872. and then of Great King <hi>Alfred</hi> 872. then <hi>Edward</hi> the Elder, <hi>Anno</hi> 901. and thence each King have their Coyns and Stamps annext with their Effigies, the moſt early notice we meet with of Riches amongſt them, is cited by <hi>Speed</hi> from <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> viz. That <hi>Oſwald</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 634. at a Solemn Feaſt, ſent to the Poor at his Gates, not only the Meat provided for himſelf, but commanded the Charger of Silver wherein it was, to be broken, and divided amongſt them; <hi>Speed</hi> fol. 303. cites <hi>Beda</hi> again, That <hi>Oſwy</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 643. ſued to <hi>Penda</hi> King of <hi>Mercia</hi> for Peace, and offered him infinite Treaſure and precious Jewels, which <hi>Penda</hi> rejected; and <hi>Anno</hi> 655. <hi>Oſwy</hi> overthrew and killed <hi>Penda</hi> in Battel: <hi>Holinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> fol. 113. ſays, That about <hi>anno</hi> 650. <hi>Oſunus</hi> Brother of <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> obtained Peace of <hi>Cadwallo</hi> by great Gifts of Gold and Silver. Fol. 119. ſays, <hi>Egbert</hi> King of <hi>Kent,</hi> and <hi>Oſwy</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> ſent <hi>Wighart,</hi> a Prieſt of good Reputation to the Pope, about <hi>anno</hi> 666. with great Gifts and rich Veſſels of Gold and Silver, deſiring that <hi>Wighart</hi> might be Ordained Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury. Speed</hi> fol. 227. The <hi>Kentiſh-Men</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 690. bought their Peace of <hi>Ina</hi> the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> King, for 30000 Marks of Silver; this <hi>Ina</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 727. new-built and garniſhed the Abby of <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> and eſpecially the Chappel with Gold, Silver and rich Ornaments, as Altar, Chalice, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, Candleſticks, Baſon for Holy Water, Bucket, Images, and all for the Altar; ſo as the Gold therein beſtowed, amounted to 333 pound weight of that Mettle, and the Silver to 2835 pound weight, beſides precious Gems Embroach'd upon the Celebrating Veſtments, fol. 313. So <hi>Offa</hi> King of <hi>Mercia, anno</hi> 775. gave Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> rich Gifts to make <hi>Alban</hi> a Saint, built him an Abby <hi>anno</hi> 795. with Revenues to maintain 100 Monks. <hi>Holinſhed</hi> fol. 132. he cauſed his Saints Bones to be put in a rich Shrine adorned with Gold and rich Stones; both theſe Kings went to <hi>Rome</hi> and gave the Pope <hi>Peter Pence</hi> of their ſeveral Kingdoms, which <hi>Baker</hi> fol. 6. calls the King's Alms; enjoyning every one of thoſe Kings Subjects, who had in their Houſes the value of 20 pence in one ſort of Goods, to pay a Penny to the Pope.</p>
            <p>There lies before me a Paper of Collections concerning Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110068:6"/>of the Wealth of England in Silver and Gold, in all the times of our preſent period; <hi>viz.</hi> till the Reign of King <hi>Hen</hi> 3. but I forbear (for brevity-ſake) to inſert them here; but will proceed to examining and collect the value and weight of rich Mettles, and the Money of thoſe Times.</p>
            <p>The Kings might acquire ſome Riches and Money, but the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple paid their Taxes and Fines for their Offences in Cattle or Corn; and that there might be more diſpatch and leſs diſpute in ſuch Caſes, a Book of Rates was eſtabliſhed amongſt them, as by the Annals of Dr. <hi>Brady, fol.</hi> 64. they knew the name of skilling, and had two ſorts of them, one ſort of two Thrimſas, as another of three. And this their Book of Rates ordained, that a Steer of twelve months old ſhall be a valuable payment or ſatisfaction for a leſſer Skilling of 2 Thrimſas; and a Stter of 16 month's old for a greater skilling of 3 Thrimſas; and ſo a Cow and her Calf for two ſuch Skilling and an half, two Plough-Oxen for five Skillings, one good Ox for three skillings, a Steer of four years old at 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a ſound Horſe for 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a Mare of <hi>Coition</hi> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s,</hi>
               </abbr> This I take to be ſome Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that the Saxon Money at their firſt Conqueſt was counted a pound <hi>Troy</hi> of twelve Ounces in weight to every pound of their Money, ſo counted in the Expences of <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> and that is ſomewhat more than three times the weight of our laſt Money, of the heavieſt; and that the Silver of that time was ſeven times the value of that Mettle in our time: Whence three times ſeven being Twenty one, it ſeems their Money or Skilling was at leaſt the value of twenty times our preſent Money; and let us examine our quoted Prices by this Rule; <hi>viz.</hi> a Steer of a year old at a Skilling of our twenty or twenty one, one ſixteen months old at a like rate of the greater Skillings, a Cow and her Calf for 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> comes to 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 13 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> at increaſe of 21. two Plow-Oxen 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> makes 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> at our proportion; a good one 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> makes 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a ſound [work] Horſe at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> makes 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a Mare at 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> makes 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> theſe Rates ſhew that I am rather ſhort of the value of thoſe times than beyond it. And for Corn, their Book of Rates ſet 30 Scheſſils of Rye, 40 of Barley, and 60 of Oats, each at a like rate, <hi>viz.</hi> each to paſs at the value of a Skilling of 3 Thrimſas; if we take theſe Scheſſils for Pecks, here would be 30 Pecks of Rye for 21 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and Barley at little more than 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> a-peck, and Oats at a little more than a Groat a-peck; whence the proportion of 1 to 21. ſeems rather too little than too much: I cou'd go on, and ſhew, that in ſucceeding times, to that of King <hi>Alfred,</hi> who reigned from <hi>Anno</hi> 872. to 901, the Plenty of Silver increaſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110068:6"/>and its value and eſteem fell from 7 times our value, to 5 times our value; their weight held ſtill the ſame, to be 3 times as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy as ours, but the value was then but 5 times more than ours: Whence values of <hi>Alfred</hi>'s Time, were to Ours but as 15 to 1; ſo as a Jurors 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a year then, was equal to 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a-year now: The Value of Silver went on decreaſing, as the Mettal grew more plentiful; and King <hi>Athelſtan,</hi> Grandchild to <hi>Alfred,</hi> who reigned till 940. made a Law, that if any one above the Age of 12 years ſtole above the value of 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> he ſhould be attached for Felony: This 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> was the value of 15 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> in <hi>Alfred</hi>'s time; not ſo at the making of this Law, but of about 14 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and yet ſtill it ſtands <hi>in terminis,</hi> as a Snare to <hi>Jurors,</hi> who will not hang a ſmall Thief; and therefore though it appear clearly that the ſtolen Goods are worth 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> or more, they do ordinarily ſay upon their Oaths that they are worth but 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> or 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> which ſtands need of a redreſs by reſtoring the old value, as other things alſo do: Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences may be collected of Silvers decreaſing in value till the end of our preſent Period, and by what degrees; but, for brevity, we are contented, at preſent, to ſay it did ſo: The pound of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in Money ſtill continued the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> every pound in Money weighed a full pound <hi>Troy,</hi> or 12 ounces in weight, and every ounce of Silver was in the End of King <hi>Henry</hi> III.<hi>'s</hi> Reign valued at 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> We have taken his Reign for the beginning of our laſt Period, during which we may hope to find more certain Aſſiſtances from our Acts of Parliament, than we had in the former Period.</p>
            <p>In our way, we may take notice, that when the <hi>Saxons</hi> came firſt into <hi>England,</hi> and prevailed over the <hi>Roman</hi> Province there, the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> ſettled themſelves in <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Lombards</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Allemans</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Franks</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> and that all thoſe Nations were <hi>Nortmans,</hi> and had one Fountain or Original, who brought out of their Common Country much the ſame, or the like Cuſtoms one of them to the other, alſo the like weights and uſages about their Money; a pound <hi>Troy</hi> of Silver being coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and called a pound of their Money amongſt their ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and when any of them lightned their Money, and made it currant at an higher rate than the uſual, the bordering Nations were forced to do the like, for keeping their own Coin in their own Countries, which otherwiſe was likely to be tranſported into thoſe Parts or Places, where the Money was lightned or paſt at an higher Account, and conſequently was of a leſs intrinſick worth and power, than the heavier or lower rated Money continued to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110068:7"/>be; and that made the Foreign Merchants deſire it, as the moſt profitable Commodity that they could obtain. <hi>Cambden</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, 40. Printed, <hi>London,</hi> 1614. <hi>p.</hi> 200. tells us the <hi>Saxon Engliſh</hi> Money was pence, each weighing our penny-weigh <hi>Troy,</hi> of which 20 go to an ounce, and 12 ounces to the pound of their Money, which is ſomewhat above 3 times the weight of our preſent Money; and this is both declared and confirmed to us by Acts of Parliament made in the beginning of this Period; <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſa panis &amp; cervitiae,</hi> 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>in Anno</hi> 1266. which ſays, that by the Conſent of the whole Realm of <hi>England,</hi> the meaſure of that King was made; that is to ſay, that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> peny called a <hi>Sterling,</hi> round and without any clipping, ſhall weigh 32 Wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns out of the mid'ſt of the Ear, and 20 pence do make an ounce, and 12 ounces one pound. and this Statute ſays, the King did ſo ordain upon ſight and peruſal of former Ordinances made by his Progenitors concerning money and meaſures: This Statute gives evidence of the value Money then bore, by the Prices of Corn therein mention'd; ſaying, that when a Quarter of Wheat is ſold for 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> Bakers ſhall make their Bread of ſuch a weight; and ſo for the Prices of Wheat at ſeveral Rates, up as high as 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarter; if we compute at a <hi>Medium,</hi> we may probably collect that what was then ſold <hi>communibus annis,</hi> for 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the quarter: It mentions alſo the ſelling a quarter of Barley for 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> or 2 <abbr>s.</abbr> and a quarter of Oats for 16 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> which proves not only that their Money was of much greater weight than ours, but that Silver was then leſs plentiful, and more valuably eſteem'd than of later times it hath been.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the I. Son of King <hi>Henry, An.</hi> 31. of his Reign, <hi>Dom.</hi> 1302. ſays the ſame over again in Parliament, by Conſent of the whole Realm of <hi>England,</hi> the King's Meaſure was made; ſo that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Peny, which is called the <hi>Sterling</hi> round, without clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſhall weigh 32 Grains of Wheat well dried, and gathered out of the mid'ſt of the Ear, and 20 pence make an ounce, and 12 ounces make a pound: And thus it appears, that Money of that time continued of the ſame weight, which it had held from the beginning of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>We find that the 32 Grains of Wheat are now changed into 24 Grains by Cuſtom, for any thing that I can find, and it ſeems with relation to Grains of Barley; upon which Apprehenſion I tried in Gold weights 32 fair Grains of Wheat againſt 24 large Barley-Corns, and found them of ſo near weight to one another, as they may very well paſs for Equals.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110068:7"/>
            <p>And for farther declaring the value of Silver at that time, <hi>Coke</hi> 2<hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> Inſtit. Fol.</hi> 506. ſays, the value of Silver in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> III. and his Son King <hi>Edward</hi> I. was rated or eſteemed at 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the ounce; and now, ſays he, it is riſen to 3 times that value; <hi>viz.</hi> to 5 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> ounce: And, ſince <hi>Coke</hi>'s time, we find it ſtill advancing in value; <hi>viz.</hi> 5 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> ounce is advanced to 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s,</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d,</hi>
               </abbr> 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s,</hi>
               </abbr> 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d,</hi>
               </abbr> and 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s,</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d,</hi>
               </abbr> and daily riſing and growing upon us: By what degrees, and in what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular times the weights of our Money have diminiſhed, and the values of Silver have been exalted, may be beſt found out by Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures made at the Mint, in the times of our ſeveral Princes; but what our Acts of Parliament mention concerning them, are intended here to be collected. The value of Silver in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> I. was 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the ounce, or 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the pound, after which <hi>per</hi> Statute, 37 <hi>Edward</hi> 3. no Goldſmith ſhall take for the price of a Silver Veſſel more than the price of 2 Marks, <hi>Paris</hi> weight, for a pound of Silver, and for this, he ſhall take but 18 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> for the faſhion, as they do at <hi>Paris.</hi> Here in the ſpace of 57 years, from the Death of <hi>Edward</hi> I. till 37 of <hi>Edward</hi> III. the value of Silver is riſen from 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> to 2 Marks, being one full fourth, which our Statute-Book mentions an Act, 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. and calls it the price of a pound of Silver in Plate-price, or Maſs; and this (amongſt a multitude of other Statutes) was repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Act of 21 <hi>Jacobi</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 28. and there it is ſaid, that by the Satute of <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. it was enacted that no Silver be bought for more than 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the pound <hi>Troy;</hi> ſo as by the beginning of <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was riſen from the 20 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per lib.</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> I. to 30 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per lib.</hi> in the ſpace of 116 Years.</p>
            <p>Between this Statute of <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. and the middle of the Reign of King <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. the other 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> was raiſed in the value of Silver, for bringing it from 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> to 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in the pound of Silver; for the King <hi>Harry</hi> Groats do not much exceed our Money in weight or value; and we have his Son <hi>Edward</hi>'s Shillings and Six pences, the <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi>'s, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s, of equal poize and value to our own: So as the 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> increaſe in the value of the Silver, muſt ariſe as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>For the alterations in the weight of our Money, the particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of the Times I cannot diſcover: but it hath been made plain and evident, that between the Reigns of King <hi>Edw.</hi> I. and the end of King <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. our Money loſt 2 parts in 3 of its weight, which it had in the Reign of King <hi>Edw.</hi> I. and this I think muſt paſs as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable Truth.</p>
            <p>Our Acts of Parliament do often relate to the uſages of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and eſpecially thoſe of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Paris, Stat.</hi> 28 <hi>Edw.</hi> I. 20. Gold ſhall be of the fineneſs of the Touch of <hi>Paris:</hi> And <hi>Stat. Edw.</hi> III. before, there ſhall be but 18 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per lib.</hi> allowed for the Faſhion of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110068:8"/>Silver Veſſels as they do at <hi>Paris, Stat.</hi> 5 <hi>Rich.</hi> II. 2. complains of the great miſchief which the Kingdom then ſuffer'd by carrying Gold and Silver, in Money and Plate, into foreign Parts out of the Realm; ſo that in effect there is none thereof left: Such Tranſportation is by this Act ſeverely forbidden. So 8 <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. 24. complains that Merchants, Aliens, of late, have taken up a Cuſtom, that when they ſell Goods within the Realm, they will not demand nor receive Payment in Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but will be paid in Gold Nobles, half Nobles, and Farthing of Gold, which they carry into foreign Countries; and by that means gain 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> in the value of every Noble, to the great prejudice of the whole Realm. Now there ſhall be no ſuch Covenant to pay in Gold, nor Bond, nor payment on forfeiture of the double values; and many other Statutes have been made to forbid the Tranſportation of Money, or other Gold, or Silver, but very much in vain, when a certain and clear Profit may be reaſonably expected, by hazarding the ſucceſsful accompliſhment of it; and with this ſhall be determined our Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Narrative concerning Money.</p>
            <p>We now come to conſider our preſent Condition, and the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity we lie under by the Male Adminiſtration and bad Eſtate of our Money; concerning which, there have been principally 2 Opinions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated among us, both in Word and Writing: Both Parties ſeem to agree, that the Fineneſs of our Silver in Coin ought to be continued ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which by 18 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15. is to be mixed, ſo as 11 ounces, two penny weight, ſhall be fine or clean Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, adding thereto 18 penny weight of Allay to make a compleat pound of <hi>Sterling</hi> Silver. <hi>Chamberlain</hi> in his State of <hi>England,</hi> p. 11. repeats this, as apply'd to Money; and ſays this Allay is to be of Copper out of the Fire: And <hi>p.</hi> 13. he ſays, that this is a leſs Portion of Allay, than either the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> do allow; and I ſay, it is a leſs Portion of Allay than had been formerly uſed in <hi>England.</hi> For <hi>Stat.</hi> 28 <hi>Edw.</hi> I. 20. ſays, all Silver ſhall be of the Fineneſs of <hi>Sterling. Coke</hi> commenting upon this Statute, tells us, the Fineneſs of <hi>Sterling</hi> was of 11 ounces fine Silver, and 1 ounce of Allay. And <hi>Stat.</hi> 4 <hi>Hen.</hi> VII. 2. ſays, Silver ſhall be made ſo fine as to allow but twelve-penny-weight of Allay in a pound of Silver.</p>
            <p>The courſe of Allay ſettled by the Statute of <hi>Eliz.</hi> I have not yet met with any who plead for the alteration of it; but all are deſirous, or contented, that the ſame Standard of Fineneſs of our Money and Silver may ſtill be continued. But there is a great difference and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute amongſt us, whether our Money ſhall ſtill be continued at the weight which it held ever ſince the time of K. <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. or that it ſhall now be alter'd and diminiſhed, for ſupplying or want of Money upon account at the preſent, and for the keeping our Money in our own
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110068:8"/>Country, and from being Tranſported for the great gain expected to be made of it, as being both more fine and heavy than the common Coin of our Neighbour-Nations.</p>
            <p>This Diſpute hath been managed by divers Perſons, who have Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd their Opinions and Reaſons in Print upon this occaſion: of which ſome maintain that the weightineſs of our Money ought to be diminiſhed, for the Reaſons aforeſaid; the Principal of which are Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hodges;</hi> with whom it ſeems, a great many others do concur in their Writings: And on the other part there have come to my view 2 Pamphlets, the one of an <hi>Hamborough</hi> Merchant, and the other of an <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Merchant: alſo a Book of Mr. <hi>Lock</hi>'s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Name; and 2 Printed Letters, without Date or Name: But which vulgar Opinions, do by Conceit or Tradition, impute to the Genius of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> and count them alſo to have been of his Writing.</p>
            <p>The 2 Merchant Pamphlets inſiſt mainly upon conveniency of Trade, which way being both evident and true, <hi>viz.</hi> that if for their Foreign Commodities they can be paid in our Money at the due weight, they make a certain and very conſiderable gain by the only Tranſporting it, and the laying out of it again in Countries where it bears a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Value and Eſteem, and paſſes at a higher Rate and Account than it bears, or is eſteemed at in our own Country.</p>
            <p>They do tell us, That other Nations will not ſubmit to any Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which we can make of our Money, or the Names, or Values which we can put upon it; which muſt be granted for an undoubted Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That they are not bound to receive or accept our Money at ſuch Rates or Values as it ſhall be appointed to go for in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Then ſay they, Engliſh Merchants cannot buy Foregin Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities at ſo low Rates of their New light Money, as they uſed to do for their Old heavy Money; and this alſo is an apparent Truth, but very eaſie to be anſwered, by adding to the number of pieces as many as will make their weight ſuitable to that of the Old Money.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Merchant p. 5. of his Pamphlet, puts 4 Objections againſt his Opinion for continuing our Money to be of the old weight; three of which are not primely material, but one of the four, <hi>viz.</hi> the third ſeems to be of moſt moment: They object, ſays he, If our Money be continued at its old weight and fineneſs, it will be all carried out of the Land, and we ſhall then be deprived of all our Money. He anſwers, That this is a very certain truth: I reply, if that be ſo true, it is better to lighten our Money, than to fall under this diſmal conſequence; yea, but ſays he, if you owe, you muſt pay your Debts in good Money, and ſo ſay I; we may do and will in our light Money, ſupplying ſtill the defect in weight by increaſe by the number
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110068:9"/>of pieces, which will ſet the Ballance of Foreign Trade equal upon all occaſions. Mr. <hi>Lock</hi>'s Book upon this Subject, was Printed <hi>anno</hi> 1695. in it p. 4. he aſſerts, That Silver is ſuch a meaſure of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, as cannot be varied by putting more or fewer grains of Silver into pieces of a known Denomination: That it hath been actually, and often done, appears plainly in our Hiſtory and Practice.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſeems to make it <hi>quaſi</hi> a natural, unalterable meaſure of Commodities; whereas Silver it ſelf is but a Commodity, and may be, and divers times hath been altered and limited in its Value and Power, by the poſſitive Laws of Princes and Countries, as they thought might ſerve their occaſion; or as the plenty or ſcarceneſs of that Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may have required. Page 8. he ſays, That the uſe of Coining Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is to aſſure Men what quanity of Silver they give to, or receive from one another; I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, this ſeems a miſtake; for tho' one may, by thinking, draw this uſe out of it, yet it is at leaſt another main uſe of it to aſſure Men, that they receive in Barter ſuch a Commodity as will paſs from them at the ſame price and value as they received it at; which will ſerve Mens turns in their own Country, although the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Stamped or Coined, be Copper, Tin, or Leather, as hath been tried with good effect upon divers exigencies and occaſions; and may be proved by the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Money before ſpecified. More he ſays, That any one may refuſe Money any way robbed of its due weight of Silver: if it be ſo by Mens ill practices, I grant it; but if it be ſo by common wearing of the Coined Pieces, I deny it; and we have ſeen old Groats worn to leſs weight than of a Two-pence, that yet went currantly, and without refuſal, as long as they would hold together: So Stat. 9 <hi>H.</hi> 7.5. all Gold ſhall be currant for that which the pieces were Coined for, and ſo for all manner of Groats [afore the time of Shillings] they ſhall be currant for 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> ſo as they be Silver not clipped or diminiſhed otherwiſe than by ordinary wearing; and although they be crack'd, yet they ſhall go at the value which they were Coined for; whence it is not that bare diminution of the weight of Silver which hinders Money from going (as he ſuppoſes) but that criminous diminution of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. He ſays, Men do not Bargain or Contract for Denomination or Sounds, but the quantity of Silver made currant by Publick Authority, not quantity of Silver (which he calls intrinſick value) only, but currant by Publick Authority: and if Publick Authority be ſtampt upon a leſs quantity of Silver or Copper, or any other matter not eaſie to be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited, it will paſs as readily in the Trade and Commerce of the Country, as need be required, and far more readily than our Clipped Coin now forbidden, whatſoever intrinſick value ſuch Clipped Silver may have in it; and our preſent neceſſities make us wiſh we had but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110068:9"/>enough Authentick Copper Money amongſt us, to ſtop the Mouths and fill the Bellies of our Craving and Starving Neighbours; that it is not the quantity of Silver only that makes Men rich, witneſs the hundreds of Clipped Money which lie upon ſome Mens hands, and they know not what to do with, except they will ſend it a very great way to the Mint, and there at great loſs, take Papers or Notes for it, to be paid, they will then be told when: Thus, <hi>While the Graſs grows the Horſe ſtarves;</hi> it is not therefore the intrinſick weight or value of Silver only which makes Men rich (as he ſays) but it is rather the ſtore of currant Coin and Money of the Nation, although it lay in Braſs, as amongſt the <hi>Romans;</hi> eſpecially when their Neighbours were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided, he asks, What is the difference of paying in Clipped Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and paying in Authorized light Money? I anſwer, The one is a Payment in lawful and good Money, and the other is the contrary; and therefore one ſort will be accepted and the other rejected, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or principally for their difference of weight, but for that the Publick Authority allows the one, and condemns the other, although the New Coin'd Money ſhould be made as light or lighter than the Clipt Money.</p>
            <p>Well, but ſays he, What Juſtice or Reaſon can there be, that he who hath borrowed an 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in heavier Money, ſhould pay it again in lighter; or Covenant to pay ſuch Rent when Money was heavier, and after pay it with lighter? I anſwer, Here ſeems very good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the State ſhould Judge and Determine what ſhall paſs for a pound in Money, amongſt their own Subjects, and that amongſt our ſelves the Stamp of Authority hath far more Power to make Money paſſable amongſt our own People, than the weight of the Silver, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it fall amongſt Men of Skill, who know how to order it by way of Merchandiſe; ſo as whether the State Order a pound in Money to be made lighter or heavier, it is a pound of lawful Money of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and it both ought to paſs, hath paſs'd, and will paſs amongſt Subjects without much conſidering the difference of weight in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations made by ſuch Authority: farther, I ſay our Author, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his Care to Creditors and Landlords, not regarding the Caſes of Tenants or Debtors; Men for this four or five years laſt paſt, have borrow'd many Thouſand Pounds in Clipt Money, but he notes no unreaſonableneſs or injuſtice in compelling them to pay ſuch Debts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in heavy Money, perhaps of twice the weight; and ſo for Tenants who have taken Leaſes within the laſt five years, at which time, and during which, they might pay their Rents all in Clipt Money, and now he is deſirous they ſhould be put to pay the ſame Rents in heavy Money; and thus he takes Care of Landlords and Creditors, but the poor Tenants and Debtors are quite neglected by him: But having
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110068:10"/>now offer'd their Caſes to his conſideration, I think it reaſonable e'n <hi>to ſet the Hares Head againſt the Gooſe Giblets,</hi> and will ſuffer and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to be content with ſuch pounds in Money as our State ſhall appoint for them, without very much thinking upon the weight of them: The Learned do tell us, That our Day and Night grows from the rotation of the Earth in the time or ſpace of 24 hours: Men ask how that can be poſſible, without the Senſe or Perception by Men, of ſuch an alteration? The Dr's Reply, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Earthly Things and Proſpects move together with us unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their Aſpects. Men cannot by Senſe of Earthly things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any motion at all; and ſo I doubt not but that after our Money ſhall arrive to the ſtrength of a Circulation, none, but ſome ſuch thinking Men, will trouble themſelves to conſider how much lighter or heavier our Money is now become; but a brisk Circulation will make ſuch alteration very little ſenſible and ſcarcely to be perceived in our own Home Trading or Commerce; but will appear only in our Trade with other Nations, and the Earths motion is plainly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Aſpects which it bears to the reſt of the Heavenly Bodies which are foreign to it, and without the natural Sphere of its Activity.</p>
            <p>Page 11. For his failure of Juſtice, or fear of it, it ſeems ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as long as the State deals to all Men alike and impartially, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out favouring one more than another, in things which the Law hath put into their Power and Practice to diſpoſe of: He ſays, The States Authority in raiſing the eſteem of Money, adds no real Value or Power to it; he may mean in the acceptance of Foreign Nations, and then he ſays true: But if he mean in the acceptance of the Subjects of this Kingdom in their Home. Trade or Domeſtick Affairs, it ſhall be paſs'd here for a very clear miſtake, proved before; and by our daily Practice in Clipt Money, and Braſs Money, and all other like occaſions: He ſays, It is only the quantity of Silver that is, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally will be the meaſure of its value; if he mean one ſort of meaſure of its value, I grant it: But if he intends the only meaſure of its value, I deny it: And ſay there are two other meaſures of its value beſides the quantity. The firſt is, the ſcarcity or plenty of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity or Mettle, and that reaches to the Foreign, as well as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick uſe of it; The other is the Authority of the State, and the price or value ſet upon it by the Government; but this is more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and extends no farther than to the compaſs of their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; and he Appeals to the next Market or Shop for Trial, ſo do I, believing it will be found, that Traders will rather chuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Braſs Money that is currant, than Silver Clipt Money which is not currant; although the intrinſick value of the Silver do far exceed that of the Braſs.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:110068:10"/>
            <p>Page 12. He compares dividing a foot into 15 parts, with raiſing a Shilling from 12 to 15 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> as if he ſhould pretend, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had no more power in Politicks than they have in Naturals: They cannot alter the Conſtituent parts of Natural things; therefore they cannot alter the Conſtitutions of State, or Values of Money in it; <hi>non valet conſequentia:</hi> We find both the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> had Money before they had Silver, and it was not of Nature that Silver was made a meaſure for the ordinary value of other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, but by Authority, and Cuſtom, as it was found a Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Mettle for that purpoſe; and if any Government will at this day Conſtitute any other Mettle, or Matter to be meaſure for the value of other Commodities, they have Power and Lawful Authority ſo to do, within the compaſs of their own Dominions. Again, He ſays, That by raiſing the value of our Money, there will not be one ounce of Silver more brought to be Coin'd at the <hi>Mint,</hi> than there was before: A vaſt miſtake, for at the higher value Silver paſſes out of the <hi>Mint,</hi> at the proportionable higher price they may afford to receive in Bullion: If three ounces of Silver paſs out of the <hi>Mint</hi> at the value of one pound of Lawful <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money, the <hi>Mint</hi> may very well afford to take in Bullion at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and upon that foot, the <hi>Mint</hi> may be furniſh'd with more Silver, not only at home, but from abroad than they can work; but even then they know what to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and not only one ounce more, but Millions of ounces would flow in upon them; and as faſt as Guineas were lately ſent over to us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we took them at ſomewhat a higher rate than ordinary. He ſays farther, That raiſing the Money, will deſtroy the Publick Faith: He muſt mean at home, or abroad; to which I have ſaid, That at home it will neither be unjuſt nor harmful, and abroad, what is wanting in weight, may eaſily be made up in number; and none need be defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of any thing that is juſtly and legally due to him. Page 14. He will have Clipt Money go only for its weight. I expect he ſhall ſhew us the Reaſonableneſs and Juſtice of his deſires in this point: He ſaid it was not juſt, that Rents or Debts ſhould be paid in lighter Money. I now deſire him to ſhew his preſent deſire to be reaſonable or juſt, that Men who have for divers years been forced to receive Clipt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, if not by Compliance, yet at leaſt by Connivance of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſhould now, without any offence charged upon them, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd by an Act of State to loſe very near half in half of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> (we know) were condemned by our Savour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>ſtrained at Gnats, and ſwallowed Comels;</hi> therefore I hope he will ſhew ſome Reaſon hereafter, that may better juſtifie his Severity againſt the unfortunate Receivers and Poſſeſſors of Clipt Money.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110068:11"/>
            <p>Page 14. He requires Clipt Money may go by weight till new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney may be provided; and that I agree, would have been a very good way, but we differ very much in the price it ſhould go at; he is for little above 5 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per ounce,</hi> and I wiſh it might paſs at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> or a Noble.</p>
            <p>Page 17. Says, Exchange is the paying of Money in one Countrey, to receive it in another; true, but we call the Money given for return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money to another by the Name of the Exchange; as Money given for the return of a ſumm from <hi>York</hi> or <hi>London,</hi> may be called the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of it.</p>
            <p>Page 18. Says, The reaſon of high Exchange [or the due price of returning Money from one place to another] is the buying much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities in any Foreign Countrey, beyond the value of what that Countrey takes of ours: I ſay this his deſcription is too narrow; and that the true reaſon of ſuch high Exchange riſes from the great need which one Nation hath to uſe or expend Money in another Nation, whether the ſame need riſe from Ballance of Trade, or upon any other occaſion: He will derive the highprice which <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> now ſet upon the return of Money from <hi>England</hi> thither, from an over-Ballance of Trade which they have upon us; but I derive it from the great need we have of Money to pay our Armies in thoſe Countries, and ſupply the Expences of our Court and Gentry there; and if the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had a like occaſion for Money to be expended in <hi>England,</hi> it would not be their Ballance of Trade which could keep ſuch Exchange from riſing, from our ſide upon them.</p>
            <p>Page 22. He preſſes again, that it is the weight of Silver or quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of it, that ſets value upon it, only or chiefly. I ſay, that if our Money were Coined, <hi>viz.</hi> a Shilling at the weight of 9 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and I had about me ſuch a Shilling, and a Clipt Shilling of the weight of 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> all People and Traders will deſire the currant Shilling of the weight of 9 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> before the Clipt Shilling, though they know it to be of the weight of 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and this proves the Stamp of Authority upon Money at home, more valuable than the weight or quantity of it. He ſays, Money differs from uncoined Silver only in this, that the quantity of Silver in each piece of Money, is aſcertained by the Stamp it bears, as if ſuch Stamp of Authority ſignified no more but to certifie the People that ſuch a piece of Money hath ſo much Silver in it: But I ſay it is that Stamp which gives it Energy and Power to be undeniably currant in <hi>England,</hi> and to be reputed and taken for Lawful Money of this Kingdom, by all the Subjects and <hi>Traders</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Page 23. Says, The only way to bring Silver and Gold into the <hi>Mint</hi> [or Nation] is an over-ballance of our Trade. I ſay, the ſetting of an higher Eſteem and Power upon them by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Authority than
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110068:11"/>other Nations do, will be (at leaſt) as great a means of bringing them in, as the other, witneſs the Flood of Guineas lately power'd in amongſt us by paſſing them at an higher eſteem and value than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and ſudden damp and ebb of them, upon their violent and impolitick debaſement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. ſays, theſe things premiſed, he will now come to argue the Caſe with Mr. <hi>Lownds; viz.</hi> theſe Premiſes paſſing for Principles, or Grounds in the Diſputation, he was likely to prevail againſt Mr. <hi>Lownds;</hi> but theſe Premiſes or Principles being denied and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſufficiently, will it ſeems caſt the Scales, and over-balance on the other ſide. He ſays, Silver cannot riſe in reſpect of it ſelf. I ſay, it may both riſe and fall in reſpect to the plenty or ſcarceneſs of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity or Mettle: And have ſhewn in the time of our <hi>Saxon</hi> Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Silver was of 7 times the value of what it now bears; and in King <hi>Alfred</hi>'s time of 5 times our value; and in King <hi>Edw.</hi> I. time of at leaſt 3 times our value; <hi>viz.</hi> the ſame weight of Silver in the firſt time, would have bought 7 times as much Corn or Cattle; and in <hi>Alfred</hi>'s time 5 times as much; and <hi>Edw.</hi> I. time above 3 times as much as the ſame weight of Silver can buy in our time. And Silver (though uſed alſo for a meaſure) is it ſelf but a Commodity, and (like all other Commodities) muſt riſe and fall according to the plenty and ſcarceneſs of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. He ſays, that an ounce of our late Milled former Money, weighs an ounce and a quarter near. The Caſe ſtands thus: An ounce <hi>Troy</hi> conſiſts of 480 grains, a quarter of which is 120 grains; and theſe put together make 600 grains, whereas the ſaid Mill'd Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece weighs but 440 grains, the Shilling but 88 grains, and 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> weighs but 37 grains: Theſe 3 Sums together make 565 grains, which falls ſhort of the weight of an ounce and a quarter by 35 grains: This ſeems a clear miſtake in <hi>Facto,</hi> which his Particle now ſeems hardly large enough to cover.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. He ſays, that by putting Money into a Melting pot one may for a penny charge make it Bullion, as if that were all; but I can cite him divers Statutes, which make the melting down of coined Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney a great and puniſhable Crime: He holds it ſtill clear, that Silver con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as Money, hath no other eſteem but for its quantity, as if <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image and Superſcription were nothing but a mark and token what weight of Silver is in ſuch a piece: but, I think that hath been ſufficiently refuted; granting, that when by clipping the Coin is ſpoiled, it is not then Money or current, and muſt have ordinarily no other eſtimation but by its weight; and as a common Comodity, he deſires to be told what Men mean, when they ſay Silver or Gold is riſen or fallen; and I referr him for Information to the Caſe and Practice of Guineas. We
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110068:12"/>ſaid they were riſen when they came to go at the rate and eſteem of 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> And we now find them caſt down to ſo low a rate, as Men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford to ſell it at the rate, but chuſe rather to let it lie upon their hands: Who pull'd down the value of them but the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ſurely they who pull down the value can raiſe the value of Mettle or Money, with or without altering the quantity or weight of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 29. He puts a Caſe of coining a Crown-piece into 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> but (intending to ſave that labour) I ſay, let the Government ordain ſuch a Crown-piece ſhall go at the rate or value of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and then it may buy ſuch an ounce of <hi>Bullion,</hi> which it could not do when it went but at the rate of 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> here: But then thoſe who tranſported it to foreign places make 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> of it, when they get it out of <hi>England,</hi> where ignorant or intereſted men are pleaſed to ſet a lower rate upon their own money, than all the Nations round about them do: And it is that pernicious Fallacy which I deſire to manifeſt, and to my ſmall power to rectifie and reform.</p>
            <p>He calls a change of value by the Government a change of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination; but we ſee the thing to be more than ſo: We call Guineys by the ſame name ſtill; and yet, by Act of State, their value hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a very important change and diminution; and if in <hi>Nov.</hi> or ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the State will ordain that their value ſhall riſe, immediate Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution will follow, to the benefit of the Kingdom, Court, and Army, for whoſe gain and benefits (by a miſtake in Politicks) the great alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was made, at a time when clipp'd money was forbidden to go, and very little new or current money can be met withal in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 30. He ſtands upon his own ground, <hi>viz.</hi> that the value and quantity of <hi>Silver</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> money] are the ſame thing utterly denied and refuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 31. He would infer, that clipp't money doth not go like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipp't only for its defect in weight. I ſay it is becauſe that one is lawful, and the other not,; and if by wearing, money loſe as much as by clipping, it muſt ſtill go as well as new money, though the laſt be much heavier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. Laws made againſt Exportation of Money or Bullion will be all in vain [if there be clear profit to be gotten by it.] He denies Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> his Aſſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> that whilſt we continue the preſent weight and value of our money, it will cauſe the melting or exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it till we ſhall have little or none left. I think <hi>Lownds</hi> ſaid trueſt in this; and Experience confirms it, we have very little left at this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 38. Our Author inſiſts, making our money lighter will not hinder the Exportation of one ounce of our Silver. I ſay it will hinder many ounces of it; but we muſt diſtinguiſh in tht places of our Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110068:12"/>It would not hinder the Exportation of it into <hi>Flanders,</hi> for the payment of our Army, and ſupport of the King and Court, becauſe that is of neceſſity, and will require money of one ſort or other, be the ſame heavier or lighter; but the light'ning our money will hinder the Exportation of it to other places, by making it rather a loſs than profit to thoſe who ſhall ſo tranſport it. He ſpeaks of having more money in <hi>Flanders</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> than we have occaſion to uſe there: This ſeems an abſurd ſurmiſe, whilſt we have ſuch <hi>Tugs</hi> to maintain in thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 39. He will needs attribute that charge and loſs to our Trade, which truly belongs to the charge of our Court and Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 47. He ſpeaks of thoſe who have great ſums of weighty money horded up by them, <hi>parturiunt Montes, naſcitur Mus,</hi> the product hath hitherto proved very ſmall, which makes the conſequence of no great hope, but is like to paſs amongſt other miſtakes in Politicks amongſt us. He ſays, ſuch men would upon light'ning our money, pay that for 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> which they received for 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> I ſay if their old 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> weigh as much as the new 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> there is no wrong done at all, by our Author's own Rules; for here the 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> have the ſame intrinſick value; <hi>viz.</hi> weight, with the new 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> which he will have to be the only Rule in money; and ſo there can be no gain by him, who gives 4 heavy ſhillings for 5 light ones; nor a real loſs to him who ſo receives them, but an equal Market between them both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 48. He asks, who ſhall get by the coining of our new money lighter? I anſwer; the intent of light'ning our money, is not to make a profit or gain to any body, but primely or only to keep <hi>Engliſh</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Kingdom, as far as our warlike Expences will give us leave. He ſays, the Debtor or Tenant can have no benefit by it; and I ſay, the Creditor or Landlord can have no Loſs by it, for that each ſhall pay and be paid ſo many pounds of lawful money of <hi>England,</hi> without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality or fraud whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 50, Speaks much of a difference of buying and paying with old or new money: All which (if I may adviſe) ſhall be put out of doors, and all the heavy money in <hi>England,</hi> both old and new, ſhall be brought into the King's hands for payment of his Army in foreign parts; he providing new and light money, and paying the Owner of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy money a weight for weight in his new and light money, and of an equal fineneſs, <hi>viz,</hi> the fineſs of <hi>Sterling.</hi> His Pages to 54 are before anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 56. He ſays, 'tis impoſſible that <hi>Bullion</hi> ſhould ſell for a fifth part above the price of coined Silver. I ſay, it is no more impoſſible, than that a State which muſt be deſtroy'd, ſhould be very imprudent or corrupt. We read, <hi>Quos perdere vult Jupiter, dementat;</hi> a State may
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110068:13"/>be ſo foolliſh, or purſue an intereſt ſo far, as to ſet their Coined Money at ſo a lower rate, than they can buy Bullion for again, to keep their <hi>Mint</hi> in going.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 58. He ſpeaks of a natural value between Bullion and Coin, and that it is every where equal, bating the charge of Coinage: I wiſh he had proved it, particularly, to be ſo in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 61. He is again at the Authority of the State, That it gives no effective value to Coin, but only a bare denomination, enough confuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 64. His Diſcourſes here upon Trade, muſt be apply'd to Foreign Trade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 65. Says ſounds cannot give weight to Silver, true; but the Authority of a State may give value and Power to their Coins, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and in their own Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 69. Goes all along upon his own rate, that nothing is really conſiderable in Money, but the weight; and that the Authority of the Government is really no more but to give it a denomination, which muſt be a miſtake, unleſs it be only intended for Foreign Trade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag</hi> 70. Says, If the State may raiſe the value of Money to ſo much, than why not to ten times ſo much; and where muſt they ſtop? I ſay, The ſupream Power of a State can have no ſtop, <hi>ab extra;</hi> but their ſtop, as well as their proceeding, lies in their own Diſcretion, and Divine Influence.</p>
            <p>Page 71. The Power that a State hath to make what Money they pleaſe currant in their own Countries, and at what value and eſteem they pleaſe, hath been ſufficiently argued againſt him.</p>
            <p>Page 73. He denies that the Market price of Standard Bullion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, or ever can be 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 7 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> of lawful weighty Money the ounce; his term of weighty, ſeems to be of little weight in this place, and his aſſertion that Bullion never can be at that rate, ſeems a little exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant; and if it be not beyond that rate at the preſent, the generalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of People, and my ſelf among them, are much miſinform'd, and do deſire to be better inſtructed, and ſomewhat more at large, and in a more particular manner.</p>
            <p>Page 74. But I do not accept of a Paper publiſh'd in 1692. as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing proof of the preſent price of Bullion in <hi>anno</hi> 1696.</p>
            <p>Page 76. He ſeems to affect miſtake; he knows that the King may tranſport Money for his occaſions, and thoſe carry our Money over Sea, and yet he ſays, as if he would be believ'd, that Bullion muſt bear a greater price than a like weight in Money, becauſe Men are puniſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Tranſport of Money, but not of Bullion; I had almoſt ſaid, <hi>teneatis amici:</hi> here he takes no notice that melting down our Coin is prohibited, and puniſhable by Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:110068:13"/>
            <p>Page 79. He ſhews from Mr. <hi>Lownds,</hi> the conſtant practice of our Anceſtors, in making our Money lighter, from time to time by Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Publick Authority, without denying or ſcrupling the Truth of it, and this Table ſhews the degrees by which our Money was lighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till it came to our preſent Standard; and thence I gather that what hath been done in ſo many Kings times, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſix or ſeven Kings Reigns, and divers times in ſome Reigns, to the number of 14 times in all from King <hi>E.</hi> 2. a thing ſo often practiced as a remedy upon Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, may ſtill be practiced and followed upon the like occaſions, as warranted by an undoubted ſeries of Examples in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Page 80. He wiſhes that Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> had ſhewed the occaſions and effects of ſuch lightening of our Coins. I deſire he will take pains to ſhew us that ever it had an ill effect; we find it always continued and proceeded, without once going back to make it heavier; which proves it was always found good for the Nation: He ſays King <hi>H.</hi> 8. raiſed the value of Coin four times, yet the Nation was not enriched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and the like, I ſay, may happen in our times; it will do fair if it ſave us from ruin, as it might help to do in his time: He had often coſtly Wars in Foreign parts, as we now have; but never ſo long and conſtant as ours, yet enough to hinder the Nation from growing rich by all the poſſible Induſtry or Caution that could be uſed; and yet I think, our Charge is greater at preſent, than ever his was; and the lightening of our Money not to be expected to enrich us, but if it help to ſupport us, that will make it enough deſirable.</p>
            <p>Page 81. If our Coin was made heavier in time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and this is the only time, <hi>rara avis in terris;</hi> and proves alterations of value by the State, are Powerful and Effectual, far exceeding a denomination, or being only a Mark or Token what ſuch a piece of Money muſt weigh; This being done but once in 1000 years, and the lightening done 14 times in the ſpace of about 300 years, proves it very rarely profitable to encreaſe the weight of our Money, but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and commonly beneficial to lighten it; which hath not now been done ſince Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, the ſpace of about 90 years, during which time our Neighbours have made great alterations both in the weight and fineneſs of their Moneys.</p>
            <p>Page 82. Suppoſes, or ſurmiſes a corrupt practice in the Officers of the <hi>Mint,</hi> but offers no Proofs of it; ſo I paſs it, as his ſuſpicion, and of little moment in the preſent Diſpute.</p>
            <p>Page 83. Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> had ſaid, That the improvement of value in Money in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. time, roſe by making their Silver finer, which was grown very courſe in the time of King <hi>H.</hi> 8. Our Author ſays, Let me add, or by the quantity leſſened in Silver. which is the ſame thing; I ſay they are not the ſame thing; for the fineneſs of Silver, and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110068:14"/>weight of Silver, are very different things, and different grounds for the alteration and reformation of Money, when the Silver is courſe and Men will leſſen the Allay, and fill the want of its weight up with fine Silver; they had need raiſe the value and eſteem of the piece ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and this was the caſe in time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. without increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the weight of the old Money at all, but making it finer; and this Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> ſays plainly: And therefore we will not let our Author add, or by the quantity of Silver leſſened; we refuſe to accept of the addition, but reject it, as <hi>mala expoſitio quae corrumpit textum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 84. He ſays true, Money was often raiſed in value, temp. <hi>H.</hi> 8. by reaſon of Expence in Foreign Wars; and I add, it was then alſo made much courſer by the quantity of Allay. I wiſh our new Coined Money have no part of that imperfection; the longer the Standard hath continued the ſame for the weight and fineneſs of our Money, the more need there is now to alter it, that it may ſuit with our Neighbours, who have altered theirs more than once in this time.</p>
            <p>Page 85. He ſees no reaſon to think that a little bigger or leſs ſize in pieces Coined, is of any moment one way or other; nor I neither, <hi>Sed plus vident oculi quam oculus;</hi> the Governments impoſition of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon Silver, or Gold, or Braſs, is of very great moment; and ſo upon every parcel, or Coined piece of them, to make them currant at a leſſer or greater rate and value, as to their Diſcretions ſhall ſeem convenient, and the Benefit and Government of their People may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; and he thinks the keeping of our Money to its old weight and fineneſs can do us no harm: I have quoted him Acts of Parliament, teſtifying that by reaſon of the weight of our currant pieces of Gold, Merchants truck by ſpecial Bargain to be paid in Gold, and by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting it gain'd 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> in every Gold Noble, or a full 4th of the value. And another Stat. complaining that our Money was ſo tranſported, that little of it is left in the Land; and our own ſad Experience doth aſſure the generality, and may convince all, who are not in an Intereſt, that all King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Mill'd Money that went in Trading, or could be compaſſed by Trading, or would be ſold at 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> profit, is gathered up, where it could be gotten, or would be ſold and tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Foreign parts for profit, made out of its over weight, as the Stat. of <hi>H.</hi> 6. ſays, there is little of it left in the Land, and none but what was preſerv'd in the hands of Hoarders, and in theirs, hardly a twentieth part of that which our miſtaking Politicians have computed upon; and perhaps not a fortieth part of it. This ſhews and proves the deſtructive effects of having our Money heavier or finer, than our Neighbours; and he that will not ſee, or feel, or hear, cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded by any ſuaſive Arguments, however concluding they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to other Men.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110068:14"/>
            <p>His pages from 85. to 91. concerning counting by a New Coin, are not of much concern in our Argument, and may be ſolved after upon a new account.</p>
            <p>From 91. to 97. Concerns only Gold, which may be conſidered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 97. He ſays, Whilſt the <hi>Chequer</hi> receives Clipt Money, he ſees not how it can be ſtopt from paſſing; I ſay the Parliament have done more than he thought could be done, by making it paſs to the <hi>Chequer</hi> when it could paſs no where elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 100. He will not have Clipt Money currant one moment longer, agreed; but he will have it have it paſs for no more than its weight in Bullion; I think this hard and unjuſt: He hath bemoaned the loſſes which Creditors and Landlords may be ſuppoſed to ſuffer by raiſing the value of our Coin, or deminiſhing the weight of it; but then he took no care of Debtors, who had borrowed Clipt Money, and were to pay again in heavy Money; he had no ſenſe for them, but only for Creditors and Landlords; the Tenants and Debtors do not need or deſerve his conſideration leſs than Creditors and Landlords; but they are not ſo fortunate, or ſo much in his favour: And now it ſeems he thinks fit as his Lord, the Men of State, and the Parliament do, that the King ſhould be recompenced for his loſſes ſuſtained by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our Clipt Money; but the poor Subjects who are ſo unfortunate as to have received Sums of Clipt Money (how great ſoever) by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or at leaſt connivance of the State, without any offence or fault of their own: Theſe men he dooms to have no part of their loſſes born by the reſt of their Fellow Subjects; but he thinks fit that all theſe Unfortunate ſhould bear every one his own loſs, to the quantity of near half in half, to the ruine, as it may fall out, of their Fortunes, and bitter grief of their minds, and openining of their mouths in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt his hard heartedneſs, and the ſmall conſideration and equity of the Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 101. His third Query, Whether our Coin can ever have any value above Standard Bullion of a like weight. I ſay, That in times paſt, it ever had ſo, and may have ſo, to what difference the State pleaſe to appoint; that it is convenient it ſhould have an higher va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue ſet upon it, than Bullion can reach to; and that therefore it ſhould always bear an higher value than Bullion of like weight and fineneſs to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 102. We muſt ſtay, he ſays, for executing of his Propoſals, till our over-ballance of Trade ſhall bring us in more Silver than we have occaſion to uſe, for the maintainance of our Armies in Foreign parts, and then farewel to the effects of all his Queries and Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110068:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 103. He agrees with <hi>Mr. Lownds,</hi> except only where he builds any thing upon raiſing the value of our Coin: It ſeems there was a <hi>noli me tangere</hi> in that; the agreeing in other things, but that, and whatſoever was built upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 104. He will agree to recoin the <hi>Clipt Money,</hi> and that in the mean time it go for its weight, as Bullion; I ſay, let it go in the mean time by weight, but at the ſame rate <hi>per ounce,</hi> that our new Coined lighter <hi>Money</hi> ſhall be valued at, <hi>viz.</hi> at the rate of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per ounce</hi> and ſo ſhall great eaſe be given to the ſuffering People, and equal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be done to all the King's Subjects; and he conceives that ſtopping the currency of <hi>Clipt Money</hi> will bring out the old heavy <hi>Money</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately; here you may friendly conclude, that either the ſtore of heavy Money is very ſmall, and far below his Calculation; or that he is miſtaken in his Politicks, in concluding that the ſtopping the currency of the Clipt Money, would bring the old heavy Money out immediately.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 105. he maintains, That ſtopping the Clipt-Money will bring the heavy Money out immediately, and without more ado: And I paſs it again for a groſs and palpable Miſtake. Mr. <hi>Lownds</hi> adviſes Charitably, that the Subjects generally ſhould ſhare in the Loſſes of thoſe who ſuffer by Clipt-Money lying upon their hands: No ſays our Author, but let every particular bear his own loſs ſingly; why ſo? Becauſe ſays he, they have profited by having it in their hands; which is a very wild and random Aſſertion, intending none but gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tradeſmen had ſuch: Whereas Creditors for their Debts, and Landlords for their Rents, have a great, or the greateſt ſhare of that ſort of Money upon their hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 106. But he is for ſtopping Clipt Money ſpeedily, and come of it what will. Well, let it be ſo, and then let it go by Weight, at the rate and value of a Noble <hi>per</hi> Ounce, that is of due fineneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 108. Whatſoever his Premiſes have been, he is of full Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Mill'd Money ſhould ſtill be the Standard, which ſhall not be at all alter'd in Fineneſs, Weight, or Value. I doubt not but that he was to be of that Opinion. at his beginning to Write, and before it, if he have well maintain'd and prov'd it (upon what is here ſaid in anſwer to him) ſhall be left to the Judgment and Sentence of thoſe who will be at the trouble of Reading and Examining our Accounts.</p>
            <p>I proceed to conſider and examine one of the Letters before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, written in maintenance of our Author's former Opinion; and generally ſuppos'd to be written by the ſame Hand.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110068:15"/>
            <p>The flouriſh of his Preface, I paſs as bare words, of no proof or real Import at all. In his Progreſs or Dialogue, he ſays, You have now Forty or Fifty Thouſand Pounds of Mill'd-Money in your hands, kept in hope to make an advantage, by paſſing 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> for 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> it ſeems this is but a bare and very fallacious Inſinuation, not able to perſwade me to a Belief, that any Man in <hi>England</hi> ever had ſuch a Sum of that ſort of Money by him; and I ſtrongly ſuſpect, that if he were put to name a Man who hath, or then had 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of that ſort of Money by him, and prove the truth of his Aſſertion (to uſe his own words) he would be baffled in it, and not be able to make out the truth of it: Men could not receive any Money of that ſort in the laſt four, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps five Years, his Sum of 50000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> at 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt, comes to 3000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum;</hi> whence the Hoarder of ſo much Money was like to be a loſer of 3000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum,</hi> ſo many Years that any Man would or did ſo, <hi>Credat judaeus Apella.</hi> Thoſe who do lay up Money do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably lay up of the beſt ſort that they have; and divers have laid up Money in proſpect of a Purchaſe, a Daughter's Portion, or the like occaſions, Sums competent; but that Men laid by them ſuch great Sums at loſs of Intereſt for divers Years, I do not believe; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of him ſome Inſtance or proof of it. And that ever any Man in <hi>England</hi> yet did lay up that Money with intent to gain by the raiſing our Values of Money, I aſſure my ſelf he never can prove; becauſe I believe it to be utterly untrue; and yet what Money Men may now have by them of that ſort, they may, and likely do, reſerve it ſtill by them, in expectation of Gain to be made, by giving Weight for Weight of the heavy Money, in exchange for the new and lighter Money; and ſuch exchange our Author will have to be no Robbery; for he conſtantly places all the Value of Money in the Weight of it, and if 80 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of the old Money weigh as much, or more, than an 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of the new, he that gives ſuch 100 for ſuch 80 will (by our Author's Rules) be the gainer by the exchange; and both by his Rules and my Rules, he who gives the 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> for the 80 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> intending to vend or uſe the Money in Foreign Parts will be a conſiderable gainer by this exchange; and he who takes 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> for 80. if he uſe the Money at home, will be a conſiderable gainer alſo; yea, and a greater gainer than the other Party, although he have an over-weight of Silver in his exchange. And as for his Debtor of a 1000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> he ſhall pay it as he took it, in lawful Money of <hi>England:</hi> If he borrow it to pay with he cannot gain or ſave a Penny, but will find the new Money as hard to get as the old was: Nor can he gain or ſave any other way, than by carrying Silver into the Mint and Coining it, which Debtors are not like to be in a condition to do.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110068:16"/>
            <p>He ſays, Foreigners do not carry away our Money by Stealth or Witchcraft, true; but he ſays, they take it for their Debt and Money that we owe them; perhaps ſome may be taken ſo, but they take it moſtly in exchange for their Commodities, or buy it up for Profit, and yet give five, or ſometimes ten in the Hundred more than the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary price, to put it off ſtill at greater Profit in thoſe Countries to which they carry it.</p>
            <p>He ſays, we muſt pay our Foreign Debts, not in our accounts of Money, but theirs; and that is true; and therefore If we make our Money lighter, we muſt make our Payment out by the more Pieces: I have always allow'd, that raiſing our Values doth not help us amongſt Foreigners, but only in our home Trades, and to keep Men from car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying our Money away; for the Profit which they make by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weightineſs of it, in compariſon with other Countries. And I ſay, that by raiſing our Money, neither our ſelves, nor any others, need be, or will be Cheated: To Foreigners it will be no hindrance, but to our Kingdom very beneficial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. He diſcovers himſelf by reciting his former Rules, <hi>viz.</hi> that the King's Image and Superſcription adds nothing, no Power to our Money, but is only a teſtimony of the Weight and Fineneſs of it, and it is only thoſe which give the Value to Money, not the King's Image or Authority. This I have paſt, and muſt here paſs for a very groſs miſtake. And I ſay, by King <hi>James</hi>'s Authority in <hi>Ireland,</hi> his Braſs ſtamp'd to go for 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> made it go there at that value during that Authority: And if our King and Government ſhall ſtamp a piece of Silver, and appoint it to bear the value of a Guinea, and be current at that rate, it muſt and ought to paſs as currently as now the Gold Pieces do, without refuſal; and no Man doth or can ſee the contrary of this, but is groſly Ignorant and unknowing in the Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of our Nation.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſays, The beſt way for uſing Money would be by Grains (which he calls Drams) Penny-weights, Ounces, and Pounds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Image or Superſcription at all: As if he deſir'd to cut off the Power of the King and Supream Authority, in the raiſing and falling of our Money: See how far Men may be drawn out of the right way, by the infatuating Affection which they may bear to a <hi>Diana,</hi> whoſe Cauſe they have undertaken to promote. Our ſtamp'd Money hath its Weight and Fineneſs appointed, as well as its Value, and may be weighed and tried as the old Talents and <hi>denarii</hi> might, but then alſo <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image and Superſcription made their current Coin; he ſays, we value Foreign Money only by its Weight and Fineneſs; and that is true: And we know and find that they do ſo by ours, and therefore deſire it. But our own Money in our own Country hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110068:16"/>been, and I hope ſhall ever continue under the diſpoſal of our Government, and the Authority and Stamp thereof, notwithſtanding his innovating and fluctuating Inventions, for ſerving of a preſent turn.</p>
            <p>Next, he puts Caſes of Foreign Trade, whoſe Countries will not ſubmit to Changes in the Values of our Money. I ſay, If our Money be the old heavy they covet it, and will ſell for fewer Pieces of it, or will buy it to carry away; the newer lighter Money they cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably deſire to carry away, being intended to be made rather at a loſing Truck and Value: This will make them chuſe to carry away their Truck rather in Commodities than Money. Whereas for many Years laſt paſt, their Practice hath been quite contrary. And there is no doubt, but that if we raiſe the Value of our Money, or diminiſh its Weight, Foreigners will ſute us with their Prices accordingly, and from ſuch Trading no Man can expect benefit by the raiſing the Value of our Money, nor ever pretended to do it, ſo as he might well have ſpared his Argnment thereupon; and what he ſays, after, of cheating the King, the Debtors, (he ſhould have ſaid Creditors, Landlords, and Seamen) to the beſt of my Underſtanding hath much boldneſs, and very little Truth in it.</p>
            <p>But next he comes to particular Inſtances, and there indeed he touches our Sore at the Quick, and ſeems to reach the very bottom of it. He ſays, If the King ſhould receive ſix millions in Revenue, I ſay, If he ſhould receive ſo much, it will make our caſe much the harder. And I had rather have it put, If the King ſhould receive five millions in Yearly Revenue; and I ſurmiſe the latter to be the more likely Computation; and before this can be rightly determined, it ſeems ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that as near a computation of it ſhould be made known as can be procured: If our Coin be required to be lightned by a fifth part or more, it muſt fall under mens Conſideration, that the King's whole Revenue muſt fall in reality to four parts of five; ſo as if before the Change, it was five millions, now it will be reduc'd to four, whence the King ſhould become loſer of a whole Million of Money every Year. This the Court, and the Men of State had great reaſon to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate and prevent, by all the means which lay in their Power; and not to ſuffer the King to be trickt of ſo great a Revenue by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky blaſt of ſuch a ſide Wind; by a Trick, which whether we ſhall call it Country and Ignorant, or Subtile and Dangerous, doth not yet clearly appear, but a dangerous effect muſt needs have followed upon ſo great a failure, if the ſame had crudely proceeded, without rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the King ſome certain and hnown, or apparently likely recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence or compenſation in another way, we ſhould never have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone our preſent Preſſures and Payments with the little murmur that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110068:17"/>we do, if we were not convinc'd, that the War with <hi>France</hi> is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary for our Preſervation and Peace. Nor would our Parliament, we hope, have conſented to ſuch heavy Taxes, if they had not found all that Money abſolutely neceſſary for the ſupport of our preſent War, and <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> Men cannot pull off ſuch a Sum as a Million from the maintenance of this War, without cutting off as it were a limb or quarter from the main Body of it, to the great endangering of the very Vitals, and hazard of its whole Succeſs. We will not therefore deſire or ſuffer ſo great a Sum to be cut off from the maintenance of our preſent War; nor can we ſuffer the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick and very evil management of our Money, and the grievous Groans and Afflictions of all ſorts of People thereupon, bardly any longer; the reducing Guineas to a Price that even puts them down, and cauſes them to be Exported faſter than ever they were Imported, and at the ſame time forbidding Clip'd-Money without providing new in the room of it. I deſire to know, what could be worſe contrived, or more unlucky, than theſe Junctures concerning Money, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more and more grievous every day, we hope God will provide: For amongſt Men the Caſe looks very dangerous, and we cannot yet ſee to the end of it.</p>
            <p>Our Author ſays, Creditors, Servants, Soldiers, Seamen, all muſt loſe by the lightning of our Money, <hi>Sed non ego credulus illi:</hi> for I think none of them will loſe a Penny by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. He puts a Queſtion, to which I anſwer, That the more Commodities we ſell to Strangers for this Money, although meaſur'd at a leſs weight of Silver, the more Money is brought into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, inſtead of carrying it out, which hath been too long uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>Next, another caſe of a <hi>Dutch</hi> ſending to <hi>London</hi> 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in Silver, and getting it Coined there into 6000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> I ſay this would bring ſo much <hi>Dutch</hi> Silver into the Kingdom; and their moſt gainful Trade with us, will be made by ſending us ſtill more Silver, which will then go at an higher rate here than perhaps it may in <hi>Holland,</hi> as was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the caſe of our Guineas.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſays, that no Nation ever raiſed their Money, but it was to their prejudice: And that the <hi>Dutch</hi> never did, nor ever will raiſe their Money; both no more than bold Aſſertions, neither proved nor provable: It would not have been often and uſually practiced in our Nation, if our Anceſtors had not found it both beneficial and neceſſary. And the <hi>Romans</hi> found great benefit, both by lightning the Weights of their Braſs Money, and by increaſing the value of Silver Deniers. And as to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> they have no fine Silver Money of their own Coining, but only courſe adulterate Money, which none can carry
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110068:17"/>into other Countries, but to their own very great loſs and damage: But their great Trades are driven all in Foreign Coin, and vaſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money hath been uſed there to that purpoſe gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, both by Trading and by Clipping, <hi>vitiis &amp; modis,</hi> not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner, ſo as the <hi>ſuavis odor lucri</hi> came amongſt them.</p>
            <p>To his <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſay, He proceeds upon his own deviſed, but a very fallacious Rule, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Stamp and Authority of State neither doth, nor can work any real change in the value or currency of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney amongſt us; the contrary of which is true, and proved by the two Caſes of Guineas and Clip'd Money at this time, and by the Law and Cuſtoms of our Nation, and the frequent practice of our Anceſtors. And upon this Rule, That the State can make as real change in the value and currency of Money, there will, by the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our preſent Money, be no Confuſion or Injuſtice at all wrought in Buying, Selling, or any other other ways of Contract or Bargain whatſoever.</p>
            <p>He ſays again, That by former Alterations of Money never was there a Penny gotten, which he never had a certain means to know; whence his Sentence ſeems Bold and Ignorant, and ſo we ſay, Who more Bold than the Blind and Brave: But he ſhould have ſaid, not only that they did not get by it, but that they never avoided any great Inconveniencies by it; but that they often did, and that we now ſeek and endeavour to do; the reſt of this Paragraph is but Threats and Prophecies, without Ground or Proof.</p>
            <p>Next, He denies the riſing of the Values of Gold or Silver in any other parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> excepting in <hi>England</hi> only, and there he doth not deny that it is riſen: What are his Reaſons for that? Why, it is becauſe our Trade is loſt: Witneſs the vaſt Foreign Trade driven in <hi>London,</hi> at the time when he wrote, extreamly now abated by the ill management of our Money. His ſecond Reaſon, Why the Value of Silver is raiſed in <hi>England,</hi> is our Pride and Luxury; He ſhould have ſhewed, how much, and wherein the Pride and Luxury of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> exceeds that of <hi>France, Spain, Italy, Germany,</hi> or that of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Country of <hi>Holland,</hi> or elſe I cannot allow of this Reaſon any more than of the former. His third Aſſertion is true, <hi>viz.</hi> That our Expences abroad have been great, and that hath occaſioned a great tranſport and draining of our Money, but how or why that makes Silver dearer in <hi>England</hi> than it is in other Countries, I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, true it is, we cannot afford to give ſo much of our Money for an Ounce of Silver, as other People whoſe Money is lighter or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, can afford to do: But let us lighten our Money, or ſet a greater Rate or Value upon it, then may it give more Money for an Ounce of Silver, and that (ſaving our Author's Opinion) will make it much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110068:18"/>more plentiful amongſt us. He ſays, I return now to tell you, That if we raiſe our Money, the Prices of Commodities will riſe with it, true; and then it will be the occaſion of great Juſtice: I have ſaid, and do ſay, of no Injuſtice at all.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſays, The raiſing of Guineas to 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> raiſed the Price of all the Goods in <hi>England,</hi> and I ſay of the Lands alſo; and what harm was there in that? Why, they bought and ſold our Goods in <hi>Holland</hi> to great Profit by that means; I ſay, it doth not much concern us what Profit the <hi>Hollanders</hi> made of them, ſo as they bought them of us at a more than ordinary rate; and we cannot help the inconvenience of an high Exchange, or Price for the return of Money, ſo long as we have great need of Money there for the pay of our Army, and maintenance of our Court in thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>Next, he agrees, That Guineas are worth 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and that whoſo obtains them in <hi>England</hi> at 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> may, by carrying them into <hi>Holland,</hi> make 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> clear gain by them, and each of them, and he thanks the Parliament for giving the <hi>Hollanders</hi> an opportunity ſo to do; but I believe it will be long enough before they have the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Thanks of the Nation for their ſo doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He ſays, The Exchange, <hi>viz.</hi> the Price of returning Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from hence to <hi>Holland,</hi> is 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> I ſay, that ſhould not be ſo, if we could help it; but the great need we have of Money in thoſe Parts, for the ſupport of our Court and Army, compels us to ſuffer the great Inconvenience of it, and the Loſſes which we ſuſtain by it; and he ſhould do wonderful well, if he would ſhew us any way to help it; but it ſeems his buſineſs is to find Faults, and raiſe Complaints; in the mean time endeavouring only to obſtruct ſuch Propoſals as are ſtudied and intended for the remedying of them.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſays, Guineas can be Coin'd at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as well as <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> true; but would they Coin Gold, which goes at 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> there, and ſend it over to <hi>England</hi> to go for 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> there, if they did ſo, their diſcretion would be admirable, but they are no ſuch Fools, but he ſometimes admires them, and ſometimes impoſes upon them, as his occaſions may require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag</hi> 4. He ſpeaks of allowing two ſorts of Money, the one light, and the other heavy; I agree that would be very inconvenient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second,</hi> He is again at his old Principle, That the State hath no real Power to raiſe or depreſs the Value of our Money, always by me denied, and often refuted. Still he inſiſts, It is the Weight and Fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Money that gives the Value, not the Authority of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; he adds, obſerve that, I ſay, that hath been often enough obſerv'd to be a falſe and fallacious Principle, directly oppoſite to the Law of the Land, and conſtant practice of our Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110068:18"/>
            <p>The foregoing Paragraph grew from caſting my Eye upon <hi>Page</hi> 2. inſtead of <hi>Page</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. He confeſſes, That ſome <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> did contract to be paid in our Mill'd Money ſeven or eight Years ago; and that proves they found a benefit in the weightineſs of it, and yet he would not have it lighter: Why? even becauſe he would not have occaſion given Men to ſay, That <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men are like <hi>French</hi> Men, and given to change.</p>
            <p>Next, He puts a caſe upon a point of Foreign Trade and Dealing, wherein I grant our States Authority cannot prevail; for that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can only reach to their own Subjects, ſo his Caſe being granted, there is <hi>non ſequitur</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Next, he ſays, Men pretend, that by lightning our Money, it will keep it in the Nation. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Gold and Silver are riſen in other places of <hi>Europe. Thirdly,</hi> Bullion is now near 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> an Ounce. Theſe Pretences, he ſays, are the chief Arguments for lightning of our Coin, and if one can ſoundly confute them, the cauſes of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Money will be quite removed and taken away; true, they will be ſo, well then, ſays he, I will anſwer and deſtroy them all in a few words, <hi>viz.</hi> By ſaying, that all thoſe Pretences and Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are abſolutely falſe. He ſays, Bullion never was worth more of our good and unclipt Money, than 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> Ounce; I ſay, that he hath confeſt, the Voice of common Fame oppoſes him in this point, and therefore he ought to have been ſomewhat particular, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the proof of this his poſitive Aſſertion; and for want of ſuch proof, I cannot but take leave to ſuſpend my belief of it.</p>
            <p>Well, ſays his poor Spokeſman <hi>Rogers,</hi> if lightning our Money will not be a great means to keep it in the Kingdom, what other courſe can be taken which is likely to be effectual to that purpoſe? Then he anſwers, It muſt be done by a due care of Trade; but yet, ſays he, If we be never ſo buſie in Trade, if ſtill we ſpend more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad than we ſave at home, we ſhall ſoon become broken Tradeſmen; and being ſo Indebted, we cannot by all poſſible means keep our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Kingdom; <hi>ergo,</hi> if it can go to Profit, abroad it muſt go, and much the faſter for that, if it cannot go but with ſome loſs to the Receiver, it muſt go too, but not ſo faſt; nor to all places of our Trade, but to thoſe places where our Court and Army muſt be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; if, as he truly ſays, our ſpending more abroad than we can ſave at home, will bring us (as no doubt it doth) to a great ſcarcity of Money, which way ſoever we turn our ſelves for a Remedy: And that, during this War, we are driven by neceſſity to ſpend for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Army, and ſupport of our Court in Foreign Countries, how ſhall we confide in the Candor or clear Dealing of our Author,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110068:19"/>who mentions not once in all his Writings, that I remember, theſe true, and moſt apparent Cauſes of our ſpending more abroad, than we can ſave at home; but lays the whole load upon the ill management of our Trade, as if the Traders of our Nation were but Milkſops and ſilly Fellows in compariſon with his <hi>Dutch</hi> Favourites, and know not how to manage their Trades. I hope, now he is Authorized (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Perſons of the nobleſt Quality) to inſpect and direct the management of it, we ſhall hear no more from him of the ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, or the defects of it; but in his next Writings the Saddle may poſſibly come to be ſet upon the right Horſe, and where now I leave it, and therewith cloſe the preſent Examination of our Author's Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting concerning our Silver Money.</p>
            <p>But whereas my ſearch into them, did before bring me to ſpeak concerning an apparent and great loſs which the King's Revenue muſt needs receive by the lightening of our preſent Coin, and which I did not throughly there proſecute, becauſe I would not ſo much interrupt my intended Examination; now, that being finiſhed, I return to faſten a new Thred to the end of that Diſcourſe; <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> and with deſign to deliver my Conceptions fully concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>That of right and neceſity he ought, and muſt be recompenced for that loſs, I have before concluded; and my preſent Diſcourſe will be <hi>de modo</hi> of it; I have all along diſtinguiſhed between the divers occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the uſe of Money, <hi>viz.</hi> between our Home occaſions, and thoſe which we may have for expending it in Foreign Countries; and that our leſſening the weight of our Money, or raiſing the value and eſteem of it, will ſerve ſuch occaſions as lie in our own Countrey or Kingdom; but will not extend to the uſe of it in Countries whieh are Foreign to us: And therefore in proportioning a ſupply ſuitable to the loſs which his Majeſty may really ſuſtain by the lightening of our Money, it ſeems needful to enquire, what proportion of his Majeſty's Treaſure wuſt be ſpent, and is ſpent upon Foreign occaſions, and in in ſuch Countries.</p>
            <p>I have before expreſt a deſire to compute the King's real Revenue at the ſumm of five Millions <hi>per annum.</hi> and if I ſhall pretend to gueſs how much of this is ſpent in Foreign Countries; every one muſt needs apprehend that I have no known or certain grounds to proceed upon in it; but it muſt paſs only for a very random gueſs; I could wiſh that ſuch Expences would fall within the compaſs of two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions <hi>per annum.</hi> and I hope, if I ſhall divide the Revenue into halves, and allow one moity to be ſpent in Foreign Parts, that therein I ſhall not be found to make a ſparing allowance.</p>
            <p>The proportion of the King's loſs upon this account, muſt be ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the quantity by which our Money is lightened; which yet no
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110068:19"/>Man hath propounded to be, ſo much as to a 4th part of its weight, and yet the better to adjuſt the computation. I do venture to propound an advancement of the King's Revenue to a full 4th part of the ſumm mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> of two Millions and an half; which 4th part will amount unto the ſumm of 625000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum:</hi> This great yearly Revenue to be raiſed by new Taxes upon the Kingdom, will (no doubt) ſeem very much to a little, in the Eyes of our examin'd Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and his Aſſociates: He computing the King's loſſes by this means, at a larger proportion than that of an whole Million; but that grows from his not granting that the State hath the Power of really advancing the value of Money in our own Kingdom; an Error maintained by him in both his Writings: But I have drawn the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count down in as thirſty and frugal a manner on behalf of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as I could find ground, and reaſon to do, and do humbly ſue to his Majeſty to be contented with it, which Grace, if I ſhould obtain, yet ſhould I but half have compaſſed my deſign; for that, on the other hand, our People groaning under the heavy yoak of many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Taxes, may reaſonably demand, by what Authority I make ſuch burthenſome Propoſitions, and who gave it me. My anſwer muſt be, that I act under no other Authority, but that of equity and reaſon, imploy'd in ſupport of the Publick Neceſſities and Charges of the Kingdom, and for the ſafety and preſervation of it; well, but they may reply, Can you be ignorant of the vaſt Charges which we alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy lie under for the maintenance of this grievous and laſting War? And will you now go about to over-charge us again with new Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Taxes on that behalf? I confeſs that I do go about to do ſo; but to the great grief and affliction of my Mind; as when a tender Parent or kind Friend orders or procures a Joynt or Limb to be cut off from his Correlative, for the ſupport and preſervation of the Body Natural. Such actions muſt be done, or the Bodies, whether Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or Politick, muſt fall under apparent danger of an utter ruine. It paſſes for an unqueſtion'd Axiom, that of divers evils of ſuffering, Men may, and ought in reaſon, to chuſe the leaſt, as <hi>David</hi> did, when he choſe <hi>three days Peſtilence in the Land;</hi> our preſent State ſeems ſomewhat ſuitable, we have now the choice of three ſuch great Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſuffer the weight and fineneſs of our Old Money ſtill to continue without alteration; and upon that account, to be coveted by other Nations, and ſo all drained from us, as in truth it is, <hi>in tanto,</hi> if not altogether: Or, 2dly, To ſuffer the maintainance of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent War to fail, for want of Money abſolutely neceſſary for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it; Or, 3dly, To ſupply the King's Foreign Occaſions for Money, with the yearly ſumm of 625000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> as hath been propounded, or ſuch other large ſumm as to Parliamentary Wiſdom ſhall ſeem conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110068:20"/>and I am apt to affirm, that this laſt ſort of ſuffering by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the King with ſuch a large advance of his Revenue, is the leaſt evil of the three, by ſome degrees; and if I may ſpeak my Judgment freely (as I confeſs I am very apt to do) I would ſooner chuſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the King's Revenue by a whole Million given in new Taxes to him, than to continue longer under the raking Conſumption of our Money, occaſioned by the extraordinary weight, and fineneſs of it; and becauſe I think it better for the Kingdom, I cannot but recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to my Countrey-men, to be obtained at any ſupportable charge whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Having thus argued and aſſerted, I might well enough leave the manner of raiſing this Supply, to Parliamentary Wiſdom and Practice, and ſo I entirely do, naming only two or three <hi>Mediums,</hi> which to me ſeem proper for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ſeems, the doubling our Tax upon Windows, ſo as every 20 pay 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> inſtead of 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> every 10 pay 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> inſtead of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and the reſt pay 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> inſtead of 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and by this means about 200000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum</hi> may probably be raiſed. <hi>Secondly,</hi> One Shilling per <hi>libr.</hi> may be added to the Land Tax. and it be made 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> inſtead of 4, and that will certainly raiſe 425000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum</hi> more, and that will compleat our 625000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> or if this be ſtrongly oppoſed by reaſon of the inequality of it; recourſe may be had to the ſubſidy of Chimney-Money, though it may reaſonably ſeem hard, that after doubling the Tax upon Windows, Chimney-Money ſhould be clapt upon the Houſes alſo; it is apparent that all ways of raiſing Money by way of Tax, not only ſeem, but are hard upon the Subject; and the more is raiſed, the harder ſtill is the caſe upon them, ſo as no payment of Taxes is for the preſent time joyous, but grievous; though if God ſend us a good Succeſs of the War, the Product and Fruit of ſuch Taxes, we hope, may be a State of Peace and aſſurance in our Land to us and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity after us, and even to future Generations: And at the preſent, we are enough convinced, that the ill condition of our Money, and the Male-adminiſtration of it, is a greater affliction, and grief to the whole Nation, than all the Taxes which have been laid upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion during this War.</p>
            <p>For remedy of which, and the future Reformation of our Money, there ſhall farther be ſaid, That whereas our Anceſtors have, ſince the Reign of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. lightened their Money thirteen times, and brought their weight of a <hi>lib.</hi> in Money from 12 ounces down to 3 ounces and 320 grains, apparently to the intent to make it agree with the Weights and value of thoſe of their Neighbour Nations: Now we may follow that Courſe and Practice of our Anceſtors, and lighten our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Money to ſuch a proportion, as may make it a loſs, rather than a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110068:20"/>gain, to whomſoever ſhall tranſport it unto any of our Neighbour Nations: To this intent and purpoſe, it is here humbly propounded, that for the future, in the weight of our <hi>lib.</hi> in Money, we may leave out and reject the 320 grains, and eſtabliſh our <hi>lib.</hi> in Money to weigh three ounces compleat of <hi>Sterling Silver,</hi> that as our <hi>lib.</hi> was formerly divided into 4 Crown pieces, in future, it may be divided into three Noble pieces, each weighing a compleat ounce of <hi>Sterling Silver,</hi> and currant at the value of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and the half ounce pieces be Coined, each the full weight of half an ounce, and currant at 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> then quarter ounce pieces juſt currant for five groats; then Shillings of the full weight of 72 grains, then Sixpences at the weight of 36 grains, then Groats at the weight of 24 grains, or a Penny weight juſt; and by this computation, every grain of Silver will value juſtly two parts in three of a Farthing; whence three grains are worth an half-penny, ſix grains a penny, twelve grains two pence, eighteen grains three pence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by this means our Money will be known and plain, and as eaſie to be counted as the former; conſidering, that three Nobles do as eaſily count to a <hi>lib.</hi> as four Crowns; and ſo for all the reſt of our pieces, which though they are all of fine Silver, yet being ſufficiently diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their weight, Men who take them in <hi>England</hi> for Debts or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, can hardly tranſport them into other Countries, but with ſome ſmall loſs, which will (I think) work ſtrongly enough to hinder the deſired, or willing tranſportation of them.</p>
            <p>But hereupon it may reaſonably be demanded, What ſhall the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do for Money in the mean time, to continue our Traffick one with another? I anſwer, That till new Money enough of this new ſort can be Coined, all ſorts of the good Silver Money of <hi>England,</hi> Clipt or unclipt, may be permitted to go by weight, according to the rate and value of our intended New Money, <hi>viz.</hi> at an Noble an ounce; the half ounce at 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the quarter at 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the Penny weight 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and the weight by grains, as hath been before expreſſed; and ſo, he who hath weighty Money, and he who hath Clipt Money, by the meaſure of weight, ſhall be all brought to an equality, as the caſe was by the <hi>Iſraelitiſh Manna,</hi> when it was meaſured by an <hi>Homer:</hi> And thus, for a time, Silver may paſs, not as Money, but as a Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by its weight; and that Silver which hath been Honoured with the Royal Stamp, ſeems warranted in its fineneſs, and may paſs by weight as before is declared; yet with liberty to try any ſuſpected pieces of it, by Fire, or by the Sheers, or in any other indifferent, and and common manner, the cutting of a piece will in our caſe, be little prejudice, becauſe it will little or nothing diminiſh the weight of it.</p>
            <p>Farther, in this caſe, it ſeems requiſite, that when the Clipt Money that is fine, comes to be recoined, it ſhould be received into the <hi>Mint</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110068:21"/>at our ſtated rate of a Noble <hi>per ounce,</hi> and delivered at the ſame rate out again; but the Silver in Bullion may be taken in at a lower rate, <hi>viz.</hi> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> 4. <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> as the ſame can be obtained, or procured; but to be always iſſued out of the <hi>Mint</hi> at the rate of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per ounce,</hi> and ſo to be Coined at that rate, throughout the Kingdom; the rate of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> or above for taking Silver into the <hi>Mint,</hi> will (I think) bring Silver plentifully into it, and in greater Proportion than to thoſe of our Neighbours, becauſe by ſuch pieces, Silver will be ſet at ſomewhat an higher rate here, than it bears in other places; and thus by raiſing the value of Silver in the Kingdom, it is likely both to be drawn hither, and kept here, except always what the neceſſities of our War in Foreign parts will drain from us; under which Wars, no Pollicies, or Advantages of Trade can make us rich; and it will be very well for us, if our beſt Induſtry and Frugality can, and do, by God's Bleſſing, enable us to ſubſiſt under ſuch burthens, as neither we norour Fathers have known, and we are now very unwilling, and ſomewhat unable to bear; and would certainly be intolerable, were it not for the viſible and inavoidable need of this vaſt Expence, and the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of our Treaſure and Money, into Foreign Countries: We have an old ſaying, <hi>viz. Need makes the old Wife trot,</hi> even when her ſelf, and thoſe who ſee her, think ſhe is ſcarce able to go: <hi>Durum telum neceſſitas;</hi> and thoſe who ſee us, and conſider what we do, and what we ſuffer, may fairly conclude, that we do willingly and of choice, prefer our Religion, Liberty and Laws, before our Peace, or Money; and all other our Plenty, and Happineſs of our being in this World; and that our late King <hi>James</hi> was given over by God, to make a very ill and diſadvantageous choice, when he ſet himſelf to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack the Nation and oppreſs them in theſe three moſt ſenſible and vital Principles of their Affection and Government; for which (if he hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, as I verily believe he hath had, and ſtill hath very good cauſe to do) I pray God forgive him, and forgive the Nation thoſe hard uſages which have been put upon him, though they ſeem not greater than the Merit of his Provocations did deſerve; for the maintainance of our ſaid beloved Principles, he was caſt out; and for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of them we do, and we ſuffer all that hath hitherto been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of us: But ſuch demands are to be made as little burthenſom as the urgent neceſſities of Affairs will permit, and that appearing to be done, with as little Prouling and Corruption of Officers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments as is poſſible; it ſeems, the Nation will be yet willing to bear ſuch an increaſe of their Charge, as for defence of their beloved Principles ſhal upon apparent neceſſity, be put upon them: And thus exhorted, I leave them to the guidance and direction of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſluence. Our before examined Author lays a great ſtreſs upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110068:21"/>the diminution of Wages to Soldiers and Marriners, but that may be eaſily taken off, by a moderate and equitable care, in making ſome ſuch addition to their weekly or monthly Wages as the true ſtate of their caſes may require, conſidering them not as hoarders, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with ſuch Money as will reddily go from them, at the ſame rate which they have received it. Thus much for our Money of Silver, whence I proceed to our Author's Letter concerning Gold; and there <hi>pag.</hi> 1. he ſays, That Silver was then come to 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per ounce,</hi> and then terms the deſign of leſſening the weight of our Money, a ſilly Project.</p>
            <p>He ſays, That in 30 years paſt, there had been Coined in <hi>England</hi> ſix Millions of Mill'd Money, and yet there is hardly a piece of it now paſſing amongſt us; and if we go on to Coin at that weight, fineneſs and value, we put our Money into a fit condition for Exportation: He and I have before often differed, but in this point and period, we are fully agreed, <hi>viz.</hi> that the weight and ſineneſs of our Money was the prime cauſe of the Exportation of it, whereby it was quite drained out of our own Country.</p>
            <p>He ſays, The Parliament muſt take care of Trade, and provide that the Ballance of it may be in favour of our ſelves, a thing eaſie to be ſet down in words, but not one word of direction how this may be done; but which (had he any knowledge of) he ought to have diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to them: I do not think that by this exhortation, he meant, make me one of the Commiſſioners for the regulation of Trade, and then by my extraordinary, and yet unrevealed Knowledge in Trade, you may expect a wonderful improvement in that Myſtery: But yet ſays he, after all care that can be taken of Trade [or any thing elſe] if you do not ſuppreſs the price of Guineas, all the endeavour will be to no purpoſe; you muſt needs ſuppreſs their value, for if you do not, there will be no Silver Money in the Nation.</p>
            <p>He ſets down, p. 2d proportionable values between Gold and Silver, that in the <hi>Roman</hi> times the proportion was as of one to ten, one ounce of Gold was equal in value to ten of Silver: That in King <hi>Edw.</hi> the Thirds time, it was as of one to eleven; he might have added, that down to the times of King <hi>James</hi> I. and his Son King <hi>Charles;</hi> the proportion was as of one to twelve: He ſays, That in King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d's time the proportion was of little more than of one to fourteen, and that now it is grown to be as of one to ſixteen. Now ſays he, If we Coin our Silver at the old weight and fineneſs, which he ſays we certainly ought to do; but which I ſay plainly, we ought not to do, if we reſpect the benefit or ſafety of the Kingdom: And I ſay, it will be impoſſible to adjuſt the Accounts between him and me concerning the rate of Guineas in our Silver Money, until we can come to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110068:22"/>and reſolution concerning the very Weight of our Silver Money: His Silver Money is computed at the Weight of 3 Ounces, and 320 Grains to the <hi>lib.</hi> of Money, and mine to the weight of three Ounces only: And this muſt needs make a very great difference in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations concerning the proportion of Value between Gold and Silver. He repeats again, that 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> Ounce was (when he wrote) the currant price for Silver (deny'd in his other Writings.)</p>
            <p>He puts a caſe of Guineas and Silver, compar'd in very great Summs, <hi>Sed dolus verſatur univerſalibus;</hi> and therefore I will propound a more particular Computation; I ſay then, That the weight of a Guinea is 128 Grains, in other terms, a quarter of an Ounce and 8 odd Grains; the quarter Ounce holding 120 Grains; to compare theſe Grains of Gold to the Value of ſo many of my Grains of Silver, I compute, that my quarter Ounce, or 120 Grains of Silver, values 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and the odd 8 Grains value 1 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> ob. fere;</hi> and together they make 21 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> ob.</hi> then multiply this by 16 (which he ſays, is the proportion between Gold and Silver) 16 times 21 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> ob.</hi> make 344 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and theſe put into our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary count of Money, make 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> of which we will ſtrike off 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> to adjuſt my <hi>ferè,</hi> and then there will remain 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> as the true value of a Guinea, according to the Weight and Value of our Silver, which I have propounded to be accepted.</p>
            <p>He ſays after, If we Coin our Silver of the ancient Weight and Fineneſs, and cut it out into 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> ſtill the more of it will be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and the greater loſs, he ſays true, and therefore let us no more Coin Money of the ancient weight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. he ſays, If the price of Gold be not brought down, we cannot keep our Silver; I ſay, let us bring down the weight of our Silver Money, and then we ſhall keep it againſt all the efforts which the Gold can make upon us.</p>
            <p>He makes a long Objection againſt his Opinion, but it is like thoſe which Men commonly produce in like caſes, <hi>viz.</hi> a very weak one, That Men cannot tranſport Silver becauſe it was forbidden by an Act of Parliament: If that, accompanied with moſt rigorous Puniſhments, could have ſerved the turn, the Kingdom could never have ſwarm'd with Clippers and Coiners as it did.</p>
            <p>Next he ſay, Others pretend, That the value or price of Gold and Silver is riſen over all <hi>Europe;</hi> this he denies, and ſays, It is abſolutely falſe, and argues the Caſe from many Topicks, of which he gives no more aſſurance than his own Aſſertions, in which we have found divers miſtakes before; nor ſeems the Objection greatly material againſt his Opinion, nor deſerving of any longer Examination, as being rather amuſing than inſtructive.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:110068:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. He ſays again, Silver is now at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the Ounce, and if we Coin new Money to be currant at 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the Ounce, it will ſink into the Melting-Pot as ſoon as it is Coin'd, and then paſs to the other ſide of the Water, and with leſs Ceremony than he mentions; and ſo we can never hope to have any Plenty of this ſort of new Money: And I ſay the truth of this Aſſertion is ſo evident in it ſelf, that it muſt needs paſs for undeniable. He propounds an Opinion, that giving 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> an Ounce for bringing Silver into the Mint will remedy this, but he rejects it as a frivolous Opinion, to think, that to gain 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> any Man will loſe 9 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> for who (ſays he) will give 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> an Ounce for Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and then bring it to the Mint to be debas'd by the Coinage, to the rate and value of 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> tho' 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> be allow'd for the bringing to the Mint. I ſay, That herein we are perfectly agreed, and that all this is clearly true; and that the only remedy to avoid theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Miſchiefs is to be expected by lightning the weight of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the ſetting it at ſomewhat an higher rate than Bullion, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath been prov'd, and will both bring Silver into the Kingdom, and keep it there, when it is Coin'd into Money, as much as the King's Foreign Neceſſities will permit.</p>
            <p>Next he ſays, There is no way to ſink the Price of Silver, and keep our Money when Coined, but by ſinking the Price of Gold: I anſwer, that nothing that <hi>England</hi> can do is able to alter the price of Silver in other places of <hi>Europe,</hi> from whence we muſt acquire and obtain it; and therefore our ſeeking to ſink it will be a vain endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; but we can raiſe the Value of it and Money in our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and by that means draw it into the Kingdom as we did the Guineas, and keep it, by making it paſs at ſomewhat an higher Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue here than it doth in the Neighbour Nations; and this, I conceive, is the only way to bring Silver and Money into <hi>England,</hi> where it hath been for a long time too much ſunk by a low value at home, which hath been the general reaſon of tranſporting it to our Neighbours, who ſet an higher value and eſteem upon it.</p>
            <p>Well, but ſtill he ſays, ſinking of Gold at home will ſink the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, without mentioning his reaſon of the conſequence, or the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it ſhould work, which I confeſs paſſes my underſtanding; and beſides, we find by dear experience, that he was very much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in this aſſertion, for now the price of Gold hath been ſunk very low amongſt us for the ſpace of two Months or more, and what effect have we found of it? Is the price of Bullion ſunk by it? Not at all, but rather encreas'd; what then? Why, it hath driven the greateſt part of the Gold to ſeek a new Settlement in other Countries, where they ſet a greater Price and Value upon it; a Guinea he hath told us goes at the rate of 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 7 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> in <hi>Holland;</hi> and is it ſo hard to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110068:23"/>get Guineas over thither in Specie; that thoſe who have them will rather chuſe to vent them here at 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> than to ſend over, and make the rate of 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> of them, or paſs them in <hi>Ireland</hi> at 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> no Man can doubt but the ſetting this low rate upon them hath made them flie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Foreign parts again; and will in time utterly baniſh them from this Kingdom, as it hath done our Silver, and the Money of it; and then we may become ſuch Animals as his Sophiſtry pretends to make us, without Money, either of Gold or Silver amongſt us; of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we have at preſent a very bitter taſte, and a deep ſenſe upon all our Apprehenſions; and this (in a great meaſure hath been the true and ſenſible effect of our States following his Advice for the ſinking of Guineas ſo low as to drive the uſe of them from amongſt us, at a time when Clipt Money might not paſs, and New Money was not Coin'd to any degree that can be ſerviceable to the Kingdom, proving what may be expected in future from our Reliance, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſuch ſtate Politicks.</p>
            <p>In his Poſtſcript he ſays, It is aſſerted by ſome (and I have quoted him for one of thoſe Aſſertors) that a Guinea now in <hi>Holland</hi> is worth 27 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> Engliſh.</hi> It ſeems ſtrange he doth not tell us, that this muſt be meant of our Clipt Shillings, but he finds another evaſion upon that point, and ſays, you muſt conceive, that when I ſay a Guinea there, is worth 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the Exchange or Price of Return of Money from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Holland</hi> is put into the Account: This Price of return at 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> is 4 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per lib.</hi> but ſays he, this 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> to our 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> both make 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> but neither ſo doth the witneſs of his Computation agree together, for 26 is not 27, but the truth is, I dare not truſt him any longer upon his bare Word or Aſſertion, but deſire it may be enquired, <hi>per pages,</hi> how far he is to be believed in this particular, in which we may be ſoon certainly reſolved upon their daily experience; and to which, in this point, I am willing to refer my ſelf. Thus have I examin'd our Author's Book, and two Letters (all of this ſort that came to my hands of his Writing) without omitting any thing material, even to his very Poſtſcript; and upon the whole, I find a great Inclination in my ſelf to conceive, that his whole Progreſs tends rather to the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Deſign, <hi>viis &amp; modis,</hi> than to a ſincere delivery of the truth in this Matter. I have before obſerv'd, that he abominates the Injuſtice (as he calls it) in making Creditors and Landlords take Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Money of leſs Weight than Money of the ſame Denomination bore when the Money was Lent, or the Leaſes were made; and taking care about the Mariners and Soldiers Wages; by which he made ſhew of a tender and ſcrupulous Conſcience in ſuch caſes: But then I obſerv'd, That he had no conſideration of Debtors or Tenants in the like caſes, no tenderneſs for the Poſſeſſors of Clipt Money when it became ſtopt;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110068:23"/>he charges them not with any demerit, and yet is contented and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to have them expos'd to the Rigour and Injuſtice of loſing near half in half of their Money, without any Offence or Fault of theirs in the point; nor is he more Charitable to unfortunate Poſſeſſors of Guineas; for he not only conſults, but adviſes, that they alſo ſhall loſe very near a third part of their Money (how rigorous and unjuſt ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſame may be) now whence can we derive a reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or diverſity of tenderneſs and rigour in the ſame Perſon and Judgment; not from the Merits of the Perſons or Caſes which have been ſpecified; but becauſe he perceiv'd, that his Pleading in the firſt caſes might help to fortifie and maintain the deſign which he intended to proſecute, whereas the later caſes had little Influence towards the promoting of that deſign; and this made him have little or no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration for ſuch Sufferers. This proceeding proves (to my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) that theſe Writings of his were not intended for a clear and impartial Diſquiſition of truth in the caſes propounded, but rather were ſtudied for the promotion and maintenance of that deſign, which he had undertaken to ſupport: And thus we part from our Author's Writing upon this Subject, without intending any farther proceeding in this Argument, than by adding a few ſhort Obſervations pertinent to the whole caſe, which hath been before diſputed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall obſerve, concerning the bringing down the Price and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of Guineas amongſt us, the manner of proceeding for the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Debaſement, <hi>viz.</hi> when the time approach'd of His Majeſties going into the Field; Guineas were by former Experience known to be the moſt commodious and proper Treaſure and Money which he or his Followers could carry with them, but to take them in at the value of 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> or above, they thought would prove a means of ſome certain loſs to them, to avoid which, a deſign was form'd to bring down the Value of them, which was promoted in the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſe of Commons, and was there firſt offer'd with Intention of bringing them down to the value of 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and was argued in that Houſe upon that propoſal; and it were then found, that there were Votes enough inclining, and that if a greater Debaſement of them were demanded, an Act might likely paſs in that Houſe to that purpoſe; upon which, motions aroſe in that Houſe to leſſen their Value, and bring them down to 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and there it was reſted, and that value was ſet upon them and authorized by an Act of Parliament; and thus they who intended to make a Champaign, might obtain Guineas here at the rate of 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and paſs them in <hi>Flanders</hi> at 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and by this means gain 1 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Guinea, beſides the ſaving of 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of that Money, which they carried with them, would otherwiſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110068:24"/>coſt them, ſo as they might ſave and gain conſiderably by this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the rate of Guineas. But we find, that the itch and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Gain is very incident to Man's frail Nature; and it is very hard effectually to determine, thus far ſhalt thou come and no farther, and here ſhall the raging of thy Waves be ſtay'd; of which truth, the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this caſe may be a good teſtimony, for the Parties concern'd did not reſt ſatisfi'd with what they had obtain'd, but began again and preſt their deſires of a greater Gain upon their Friends in the Houſe of Commons, with ſo much prevalency as that they ſhortly after obtain'd another Act of Parliament for bringing the rate of Guineas yet lower, and even to the preſent ſtint of 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> with Impoſition of Penalties upon thoſe who ſhould Pay or Receive them at an higher Value; and having thus firmly fixt their Stakes, they weakly conceive that Men who had taken their Guineas at 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> vendible again in <hi>Holland</hi> at 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and in <hi>Ireland</hi> at 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> would come to them, and ſell their Guineas at 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> whereby our Court and Camp ſhould gain four more Shillings by every Guinea which they ſhould carry with them into <hi>Flanders;</hi> and was not this like to be a fair Perquiſite and a great Gain to our Men of Action in thoſe Parts? It ſeems, the Proſecutors of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign made their Accounts in this manner, but the effect prov'd, that they reckon'd without their Hoſts; for whereas at the rate of 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> they might have had Guineas enough to have fully ſerv'd all their turns, or at 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> might have had a great quantity of them, and at 26 <abbr>
                  <hi>s</hi>
               </abbr> a conſiderable proportion of them; now by bringing them down to 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> they were fore'd to go over empty-handed, and to draw our new Coin'd Silver over after them to ſupply that want. <hi>Aeſop</hi> tells us of a Dog, which catching at the Shaddow of a Shoulder of Mutton in the Water as he was Swimming, dropt and loſt that he had really in his Mouth before; and this effect was foretold upon the firſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> Act, and was eaſily foreſeen by many conſiderate Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> that our old Proverb of, <hi>All covet all loſe,</hi> would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be verified upon them; but I ſay farther, that if they might have obtained a Succeſs in this enterpriſe ſuitable to their Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Deſires, and by that means a great preſent Advantage and Profit, they ought to conſider it but as of a very ſhort continuance, of 1 Years ſtanding only, obtain'd to the prejudice and Grief of their Fellow Subjects, whoſe Purſes and Families bear their burthens, and the heat of the Day, honeſt and true Conſideration and Policy will direct them, that moderation in Gain (as well as in other things) will make them more laſting and durable, if Men take them ſo one Year, as they may be likely to hold out another Year, and ſo for a longer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Thus all the parts of a Politick Society may ſubſiſt and hold long together; but if they bite, and (by extorting) devour one another,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110068:24"/>they may reaſonably expect to be conſum'd one by another. Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Capacities have (in times paſt) receiv'd much Inſtruction by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, and therefore we will compare our Native Kingdom to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s great Tree, whoſe Leaves were fair, and the Fruit thereof much, and in it was Meat for all that depended upon it; and that Tree alſo was ſtrong, but not beyond the poſſibility of being cut down, and proſtrated, whereby its Leaves ſhould be ſhaken off, and its Fruit ſcattered; the Tree or Bole of our Kingdom is not ſo ſtrong as that was, but it bears, and perhaps may be able to bear) but how long no Man knows) the neceſſary burthens of our Court, our Men of State and Law, the charges of a very numerous Army, and other Foreign Expences; the Matter of this Tree is not Iron, but Wood, and though call'd a Kingdom, is a Body that hath Life, and muſt have Nouriſhment and Cultivation, without which it cannot ſubſiſt, it is penetrable, and may be coroded moſt dangerouſly by the ſtrong Saws of publick and authorized Extortion of any one part upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and every ſtrong Draught of a Saw in that kind is made with great danger to the Body of the Tree, tending to its Proſtration and Ruine, which, whenſoever it ſhall happen, muſt carry with it all that belongs to it; Court, State, Army, muſt ſtand and fall together with it, and therefore muſt every ſort of Men (that are conſiderate) make it their ſpecial care ſo to live out of this Tree, as to preſerve the Bole and Body of it ſtrong and entire, that their own juſt and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Subſiſtance and Gain may have a longer and more likely duration, and it muſt certainly be very noxious and dangerous for any, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially any one ſort or parcel of Men in it, ſo to proſecute their own Gain out of it as to uſe Force or Fraud for obtaining of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Gain to themſelves by impoveriſhing, and ſo grieving and wounding the reſt of their Fellow Subjects, eſpecially in a time of publick Diſtreſs and Calamity, and wherein Peoples Minds are more touchy and exaſperated than they are at other times; thus they may probably arrive at diſturbing the publick Peace, a near way to the proſtration of that Tree which ſupports them all, and the whole loſs of that Entertainment, Maintenance, and Gain which they receive from it.</p>
            <p>To this another ſhort Simile may be added, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Company paſſing over the Stage of this World, who ſtand in need of much Proviſion, and many Accommodations, and have Beaſts of Carriage for the Portage of them, be they Horſes, Camels, or Aſſes, as long as theſe Cattel are well us'd and indifferently Laden, they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to bear Weeks, Months, or Years; but if their Food and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender be withdrawn by ſurreption, or forcibly taken away, or if they be much over-laden, or but over-driven they will be apt to fail,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110068:25"/>and ſall under their Burthens, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid to his Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> of his Flocks and Herds, that if Men ſhould overdrive them one day, all the Flock will dye; and ſo if the People be over-driven one Year, great Loſſes and Diſturbances are likely to enſue, and then the Court, Men of State and Arms are like to be left every one to bear his own burthen, and to ſhift for themſelves, as other opportunities ſhall be offer'd them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Similies are intended to teach and demonſtrate to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Capacity, the danger which a greedy gaping after Gain (the very root of evil) may be expected to produce in a Nation ſo full of diviſion, and ſo nicely ſenſible of unjuſt or unkind uſage as our People (eſpecially in diſtreſs) are now, and have always us'd to be. My Supplication is, that Men may conſider one another, and provoke not to Anger and Clamour (now very riſe amongſt us) but to love and to good Works, ſo as Men may not look every one on his own things only, but alſo upon the things of others, a courſe which I doubt was not ſincerely follow'd in our laſt quoted Act for putting down the Price of Guineas to the rate of 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and thus ſhall the extent of my firſt Obſervation be bounded and finiſhed.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Obſervation will concern the preſent ſtate of our Silver Money. We have, beſides our quantities of Clipt Money, two ſorts of heavy Money, the one old, and the other new; and we have in proſpect a third ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> a lighter ſort that may hereafter be Coin'd, which leaner or lighter ſort of Money ſhall (if my deſign fail not) ſwallow up all the other ſorts of Silver Money in the Kingdom, where it were to be wiſht, that one ſort of Weights, Meaſures, and Money, might be in common uſe and practice throughout the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>In proſecution of my preſent deſign, the firſt propoſal in it will be the hardeſt, <hi>viz</hi> the obtaining a great Sum to be ready Coin'd of my new and lighter ſort of Money of the old and eſtabliſh'd Fineneſs, to the Value of ſome Hundred Thouſand Pounds, but that once done and ready to be paid out, it may be ordain'd and proclaim'd, that whoſo brings heavy Money into the <hi>Exchequer</hi> or <hi>Tower,</hi> ſhall forthwith, and without payment of Fees, receive new and light Money in lieu or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for it, to an equal Weight of that which he hath brought in by this exchange (Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> often aſſerts and maintains) the King can have no loſs, receiving an equal Weight in fine Silver to that which he pays out; and I have agreed with Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> that concerning the King's Expences in Foreign Parts, his Rule and Computation is true, but I have denied it to be ſo for Money ſpent in the Kingdom; and thence I argue, that the King receiving the heavy Money, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in Specie out of the Kingdom ſuffers no loſs at all by this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110068:25"/>but ſaves 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> by ſending this Money beyond the Seas in Specie, without paying 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> for the return of it, and which he muſt pay and loſe as oft as he returns Money into thoſe griping Low-Countries for the pay of his Army and ſupply of his other Occaſions there; but though the King, as I have ſaid, ſhall not loſe a Penny by this Exchange, but ſhall ſave the 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> which the Return otherwiſe might have coſt him, yet the Subject with whom he deals upon this occaſion, may happen to prove a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Gainer by this ſort of Exchange, but for that he muſt thank the Government, which by its publick Stamp and Authority, hath rais'd the value of Silver within its Dominions, and made a leſs Weight of it currant at a greater Price and eſtimation than it was ſormerly wont to bear; I ſay, the Gains which Subjects may make by ſuch exchanges with the King, will ſoon bring all our heavy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into the King's hands, whoſe occaſions will ſpeedily call for the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportion of it; alſo the Clipt Money being receiv'd into the Mint at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <hi>
                  <abbr>d</abbr> per</hi> Ounce, will ſpeedily come in to be Coin'd into the lighter Money, which will (by theſe means) ſoon become the only Silver Money currant in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Yet this Propoſal may be put into other Terms, and be thereby made a very little more beneficial for the Crown; the increaſe of whoſe Revenue in an equitable manner, I think, all ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote: Let it then be Proclaim'd, that what Subject ſoever brings in to the King 80 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in the heavy Money, ſhall receive 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of our new light Money in lieu of it; by this Exchange the King will gain 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per Cent fere,</hi> which will riſe to 45 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Thouſand, and to 225 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in the 1000000 and to 2250 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in the Million of Money; if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may make this profit (which will riſe from the over-weight which is in the 80 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> above the 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr>) I pray the Exchange may paſs upon that foot, but if his Officers or Miniſters muſt lick this petty profit of their Fingers, and put it into their own Purſes (as the caſe is very likely to fall out) then I wiſh the Exchange may paſs upon the other foot of Exchanging weight for weight of the one ſort, as of the other, ſo as the Subject may have that ſmall profit, rather than the Miniſters enrich themſelves by it.</p>
            <p>But upon the whole matter of this Propoſal, there muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a great Bank of our New Money in the King's Hand, and diſpoſal that his Officers may be able to pay with the one hand, as they receive with the other; or the Traffick and Trade of this Exchange will prove very ſlack and inconſiderable, for Men will not part with the good and heavy Money in their own preſent poſſeſſion, for Tickets and Tallies; nor perhaps upon any Credit that can be propounded to them, and therefore this Trade muſt needs be driven by the preſent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110068:26"/>Money on both ſides, or elſe the deſign will prove abortive; and in like manner for the Clipt Money, if it may paſs at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 8 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per ounce</hi> by weight, it will not readily come into the <hi>Mint,</hi> except there be New Money ready to pay for it at that rate; but this proviſion being made, all the Money, and even Silver in the Kingdom will be ready to flow into our <hi>Mint,</hi> and from Foreign parts, to be Coin'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main amongſt us, becauſe we ſhall ſet a little higher rate and value up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, than that which it yet bears amongſt our Neighbour Nations. Alſo by this means, all will be ſoon converted into one Sort and Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Money, which was the thing propounded to be perform'd in this 2d Obſervation. My 3d and laſt Obſervation will concern the dangerous and corroding Canker, which eats out the very Bowels of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Treaſure and Money, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the griping Extortion laid upon us by our next Neighbours and Confederates in the <hi>Low Countries</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders;</hi> they know we have preſſing need of Money in their parts, for the Payment of our Army, and ſupport of our Court there, and their Merchants make the uttermoſt advantage which they can of ſuch neceſſity; and therefore though our Money lie ready in <hi>England</hi> for ſuch purpoſes, or the Credit which we offer for that purpoſe, be never ſo good and unqueſtionable, they will not return this Money for us into their Low Countries, nor pay our Bills charg'd upon them for thoſe purpoſes, at a leſs rate or price than 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> allowance for ſupplying the neceſſities which grow upon us from the occaſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſt: This 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> in the return of every Million amounts to the ſumm of 200000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> whence if the King expend two Millions and an half in thoſe parts yearly (according to our former computation) and this be paid by returns through thoſe Countries, our King and Nation muſt perfectly loſe and caſt away the ſumm 500000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> for which (according to our proverbial expreſſion) the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation or People muſt <hi>Neither Eat nor Drink.</hi> This is a vaſt yearly Charge and even unſupportable to the State of the Kingdom, the very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion and remembrance of it, is a grievous and afflictive burthen to thoſe who will concern themſelves for the ſupport and well-fare of their Native Countrey; and my intent is to offer this great Suffering to the conſideration and feeling of ſuch Perſons, that ſo they may all lay it to Heart, and thence be ſtimulated, provok'd, and ſtirred up by all the ſtretch of their Wits, and Induſtry of their Hands, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and cure this miſerable Loſs, and Conſumption of our Money; or at leaſt in ſome meaſure to diminiſh or aleviate the ſame. I will therefore recommend this matter to the Men of State, and eſpecially to the Commiſſioners of the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> and next to the Commiſſioners for the regulation of Trade, and by Name to my Examin'd Author, Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> and to all other Perſons of Skill and Activity in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110068:26"/>exhorting every one of them, according to their ſeveral Stations and Abilities, to Study and Endeavour the removal of this miſerable Loſs and Calamity from us, or to make it more tollerable than at preſent we find it; and that I may begin with caſting my Mite into this Treaſury of Merit, I pretend to offer two Propoſals, each of which may poſſibly prove in ſome meaſure Remedial of this our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam'd Malady and Conſumption.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, That a conſiderable part of the Kingdoms Treaſure may be employ'd in Traffick, and for that purpoſe his Majeſty may have Factors and Factories, Store-Houſes and Magazines in his Cities of <hi>London, Portſmouth, Plymouth, Briſtol, Cheſter, Dublin,</hi> and two more good Ports of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Weſt; and <hi>Yarmouth, Hull, Newcaſtle, Edenborough,</hi> and ſome more Northern Port of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the Eaſt; and that the King's Factors buy with his Money, or ſuch Credit as they can fairly and freely obtain, ſuch ſort of Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the adjacent Countries, as are moſt likely to be of ready Vent in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> viz. all ſorts of Neceſſaries for Eating, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Wearing, and Tin, Lead, Timber, Salt-peter or Nitre, Iron, Canvas, Cordage, Coals, and other like Commodities; and that he have in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> other Factories at <hi>Antwerp, Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Rotterdam, Middleburgh, Dort,</hi> or other places for the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vending all the ſaid Commodities which ſhall come from his own Dominions, or may be procur'd by Truck and Tade from the <hi>Elb.</hi> the <hi>Baltick,</hi> or other Northern Countries, theſe vended in the <hi>Low Countries</hi> for ready Money or good Credit, may ſtop a great part of our Leak, and by degrees may make our Veſſel more ſtanch and ſteddy than heretofore it hath been, private Men have often grown rich by the gains of ſuch Traffick, but if the King make but his own of it, he'll be ſatisfied by ſaving 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> for the return of ſo much Money; nay, and if he loſe 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> in his Trade, he will ſave 15 <hi>per Cent</hi> in his Returns, and if he loſe 10 <hi>per Cent</hi> or 15 <hi>per Cent</hi> in the Trade, he will ſtill ſave 10 or 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> in his Returns; it is true, <hi>nihil ſimul inventum &amp; perfectum,</hi> and therefore Men ought to begin with leſſer trials, which if proſperous, will grow to more perfection by degrees; and if this or a like Propoſal do hit, divers benefits may ariſe from it; our Countrey Commodities may thereby riſe in their value; it may give Employments to many Subjects, and to Seamen and their Veſſels; it may cauſe our Coaſts to be better guarded, for Protection of the King's Goods, not ſuffering our Men of War to fleep out their time in <hi>Torbay,</hi> as they have been too much accuſtomed to do, but put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in active Guard, at leaſt upon our Coaſts, ſo long as the ſeaſon of the Summer and Temperate weather will permit.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:110068:27"/>
            <p>My ſecond Propoſal for a meaſure of Remedy in our beforementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned caſe, may be made, by the moſt beneficial Management of Gold and Guineas amongſt us. I have before Calculated the exact value of a Guinea in our new and light Money, to be 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> this Guinea I take to go in <hi>Holland</hi> at the rate of 27 old Shillings, (which are an eighth part better than the new) whence thoſe 27 Shillings are 5 Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings at leaſt better than our 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> if then we obtain Guineas here at the rate of 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and put them off in <hi>Holland</hi> at ſuch 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> we may ſave the whole 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> Return and Gain, beſides 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> or 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> in every <hi>Guinea,</hi> but if I ſhall count with Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> the 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> out of the 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> it will reduce the 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> to the value of our light Money, and then we ſhall buy at the value of 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and ſell ht 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> by this Mart we ſhall loſe but 5 <hi>per Cent,</hi> and that will ſave us 15 <hi>per Cent</hi> of our 20. and if we ſhould buy at 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and ſell at 27 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> it is a loſs but of 10 <hi>per Cent,</hi> and would ſave us other 10. if we buy at 31 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and for 27. we ſhall loſe but 15 <hi>per Cent,</hi> and be ſtill ſavers of 5 <hi>per Cent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Mediums</hi> I leave as Propoſals to be well conſider'd and farther improv'd, or ſet aſide by putting better Propoſals in their ſtead, and not by letting the matter fall, without procuring ſome redreſs in it, and herewith ſhall be cut off the Thread of this Diſcourſe, in which I have not ſhun'd or forborn to declare to my Countrey, the true and whole ſtate of the matters now in agitation, as far as my Knowledge can extend; and I pray God to give it a ſucceſs ſuitable to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, good Affection and Intention of the Writer, who hopes he had in it a Superior Aſſiſtance, and deſires there may be rendred to the only great Fountain of Being and Goodneſs, the whole Honour and Glory, and all the Thanks, Praiſes, and Acclamations of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110068:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
